<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unmasking of a masse-monger Who in the counterfeit habit of S. Augustine hath cunningly crept into the closets of many English ladies. Or, the vindication of Saint Augustines confessions, from the false and malicious calumniations of a late noted apostate. By M.S. D. of Exeter.</title>
            <author>Sutcliffe, Matthew, 1550?-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 213 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13178</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23473</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100147</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835999</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835999</idno>
            <idno type="VID">238</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13178)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 238)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1293:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unmasking of a masse-monger Who in the counterfeit habit of S. Augustine hath cunningly crept into the closets of many English ladies. Or, the vindication of Saint Augustines confessions, from the false and malicious calumniations of a late noted apostate. By M.S. D. of Exeter.</title>
                  <author>Sutcliffe, Matthew, 1550?-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. A[lsop] and T. Favvcett, for Nich: Bourne, and are to bee sold at his shop neere to the royall exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>M.S. = Matthew Sutcliffe.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>A criticism of Sir Tobie Matthew in his translation of Saint Augustine's Confessions.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Augustine, --  Saint, Bishop of Hippo. --  Confessions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Matthew, Tobie, --  Sir, 1577-1655 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:238:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:238:1"/>
            <p>THE VNMASKING <hi>of a Maſſe-monger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHO IN THE COVNTERFEIT Habit of S. AVGVSTINE hath cunningly crept into the Cloſets of many <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Ladies.</p>
            <p>OR, <hi>THE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>INDICATION of Saint</hi> AVGVSTINES <hi>Confeſſions,</hi> from the falſe and malicious Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niations of a late noted <hi>Apostate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>M. S.</hi> D. of EXETER.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. TIM. 1.19. &amp; 20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Hauing Faith and a good Conſcience, which ſome hauing put away, and as concerning Faith haue made ſhipwracke.</p>
               <p>Of whom is <hi>HYMENIVS,</hi> and <hi>ALEXANDER,</hi> whom I haue deliuered vnto Satan, that they may learne not to blaſpheme.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 22.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Dogges are come about mee, and the counſell of the Wicked hath aſſaulted mee.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by B.A. and T. FAVVCET, for NICH: BOVRNE, and are to bee ſold at his Shop neere to the Royall-<hi>Exchange.</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:238:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:238:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, AND HIS VERY WORTHIE <hi>Friends, Sir</hi> BAPTIST HICKES <hi>Knight, and the good Lady his Wife.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the holy Apoſtles, <hi>Right Worſhipfull,</hi> ſo all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſtians deriue their faith from CHRIST. <hi>Acceptam à</hi> CHRISTO <hi>diſciplinam fideliter natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus aſſignarunt,</hi> ſayth<note n="*" place="margin">De prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript.</note> TERTVLLIAN, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Apoſtles. Hee is the Foundation that cannot fayle, and the Truth, that cannot erre; and therefore, are the Faithfull ſayd to bee built vpon <hi>the Foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.</note> becauſe they firſt Preached CHRIST, the onely Corner-ſtone, and mayne Foundation of the Church. Vpon the Foundation of CHRIST and his Apoſtles
<pb facs="tcp:238:3"/>both S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. AVGVSTINE and all the ancient Fathers built their Faith.</p>
            <p>Doe wee then thinke, that the Tranſlator of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. AVSTINES Confeſſions a notorious Rinegate from the Faith of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> hath reaſon out of that Father to draw his Romiſh Doctrine? Sure no, the poyſon of his Hereſie cannot be found in that holy Fathers Workes. All his Confeſſions are directed to GOD, and neyther to Saints, nor Angels, nor to the Virgin MARY, as is the vſe and practiſe of the Synagogue of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Popes two Swords, and his triple Crowne, his ſupreme Power to judge, his Cardinals, Hierarchicall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Vniuerſall Monarchie ouer the whole Church hee knew not. The reall preſence of CHRISTS Body vnder the accidents of Bread and Wine, and the eating thereof by the mouth of the Faithfull; yea, by the mouthes of the Reprobate and brute Beaſts hee neuer taught. Neyther did hee teach the monſtrous Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation and the reft of the abominable Hereſies, eſtabliſhed againſt vs in <hi>Trent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hungry Dogges may dreame of Bread.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſayth THEOCRITVS <hi>in Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorib.</hi> And as ATMANASIVS ſayth, <hi>in Apolog. Defug. Heretikes forge opinions according to their owne pleaſure. Pro libidine ſua id opinâtur quod volunt.</hi> But Truth will alwayes ſtand firme.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, ſeeing this Apoſtate, ſo vnkind to his Parents, ſo falſe to his Countrey, ſo malicious to Religion, hath ſome yeares ſince publiſhed S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTINES <hi>Confeſſions,</hi> tranſlated into Engliſh, in a
<pb facs="tcp:238:3"/>long Preface, and diuers falſe marginall Notes, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations, and Calumniations, endeuouring to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the ſimple to diſlike the Truth profeſſed in this Church, and to affect and approue the corruptions of Popery, as if S. AVGVSTINE did fauour his Sect, and diſlike our Confeſſion; I haue thought it a Worke worth my labour, to Vindicate that holy Father out of this impure fellowes falſe fingers. Not that you need to bee reſolued of the truth of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, wherein I know you are firmely eſtabliſhed; but to the end, that what I write for the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the weake, comming foorth vnder the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage of your name, might remayne as a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall teſtimony of that loue and reſpect, which I haue borne and alwayes ſhall beare you.</p>
            <p>Theſe fellowes impudently arrogate to themſelues the Name of <hi>Catholikes.</hi> But, as ATHANASIVS ſaith in his 2. <hi>Orat.</hi> againſt the <hi>Arrians; How can they bee reputed among the members of the Catholike Church, whoſe Faith is not Apoſtolike?</hi> This young Nouice may pleaſe himſelfe with his childiſh Annotations and Prefations; but, I ſhall ſhow they are no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then <hi>thoſe Childiſh fables and fooleries,</hi> which S. AVSTINE, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>contr. Academic.</hi> would haue caſt out of mens hands. Nay, diuers points of Poperie are no better then thoſe <hi>monſtrous Fancies,</hi> which ORIGEN condemneth writing againſt CELSVS. And this I ſhall (God willing) hereafter plainely demonſtrate, and not onely take from him all that hold, that hee thinketh to haue, eyther in Saint AVGVSTINES <hi>Confeſsions,</hi> or in any other Booke of his.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:238:4"/>
            <p>This Treatiſe I conſecrate to GOD vnder the Patronage of your fauour, beſeeching him that it may profit many, ſo, that the Thankes may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine to you, and that thereby you may vnderſtand how much I honour you, and that I ſhall alwayes remayne:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, much obliged and deuoted: <hi>M. SVTCLIFFE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:238:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom the excellencie of S. <hi>AVGVSTINES</hi> Pietie, Vertue, and Learning, we purpoſe not (Chriſtian Reader) to derogate any thing: nay, we doubt not to preferre him before many others, both ancient and late Prelates. Let the whole List of late Popes, and their purple Cardinals, and Mitred Prelates, be produced, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with that holy Father, I ſuppoſe he will ſurpaſſe them all; neyther doe we doubt, but he is more worthie then manie others, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: yet doth hee not exempt his Writing from other mens iudgement. <hi>Id genus literarum,</hi> ſayth he, writing against <hi>Fauſtus, lib. 11. c. 5. Quae non praecipiendi authoritate, ſed proficiendi exercitatione ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buntur a nobis, non cum credendi neceſſitate, ſed cum iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicandi libertate legendum eſt:</hi> ſo hee permitteth <hi>others to iudge of his Writings.</hi> Neyther doth he diſdaine in the ſame place, to preferre the Canonicall Bookes of Scripture before them: nor doe wee thinke it any diſparagement vnto him, or other Fathers, to haue the Apostles preferred before them, as hee writeth vnto <hi>Hierome, Epiſt. 19.</hi> There alſo hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth that priuiledge to Scriptures onely, <hi>Not to erre in any thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtate doth in diuers places call him <hi>an incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Doctor:</hi> yet neuer did S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſo thinke of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, nor doe other learned men ſo eſteeme him, but that <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,
<pb facs="tcp:238:5"/>Gregorie Nazianzene, Chryſoſtome, Baſil, Hierome, Ambroſe,</hi> and others, might bee compared with him.</p>
            <p>But the more excellent hee is, the more is our gaine; the leſſe the Apoſtates aduantage. For this I affirme, and I doubt not but to make it good against all the packe of <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> and not onely against this ſilly Tranſlator, whoſe ſoule is lately turned and tranſlated Popiſh; Firſt, that S. <hi>AVGVSTINE</hi> neuer beleeued the Popes infallible judgement in matters of Faith, nor his ſublime and vniuerſall Monarchy ouer the whole Church, nor the Doctrine of the Popes Schooles and Decretals; and ſecondly, that hee holdeth nothing as a matter of Faith and neceſſary to bee beleeued, that is contrary to the Articles of Religion publikely profeſſed in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In proofe whereof, that wee may proceed more particularly and punctually, wee ſhall (God willing) declare in the first Chapter, that S. <hi>AVSTINE</hi> neuer knew eyther the Decrees of <hi>Trent</hi> enacted against vs, or that part of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion which this Church of <hi>England</hi> admitteth not, and which this Apoſtate and his Conſorts hold to bee Catholike. In the ſecond Chapter ſhall bee demonſtrated, that many of theſe Points of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion which wee reject are alſo contradicted by S. <hi>AVGVSTINE.</hi> Thirdly, becauſe the Apoſtate and his Conſorts, doe euer and anon challenge to themſelues the name of <hi>Catholikes,</hi> wee propoſe in the third Chapter by Arguments inuincible to conuince them, that they are neyther Catholikes nor hold the true Catholike and Apoſtolike Faith. The fourth Chapter, ſhall contayne the examination of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates Title page, and his Epiſtle dedicatory. In the fift Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Apoſtates abſurd tedious and malicious Preface is ſcanned and refuted. The ſixth Chapter, ſetteth downe Notes and Animaduerſions vpon the Tranſlators idle Aduertiſement. Jn the ſeuenth and last Chapter, the falſe wicked and abſurd Notes of the Tranſlator vpon S. <hi>AVGVSTINES</hi> Text, are refuted and expugned.</p>
            <p>Now how contrary S. <hi>AVGVSTINES</hi> writings are to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, here I will giue a touch in generall. <hi>Non ſit nobis
<pb facs="tcp:238:5"/>religio,</hi> ſayth hee, <hi>c. 55. de Ver. Relig. in phantaſmatibus noſtris; Let vs not frame Religion according to our fancies.</hi> But Popiſh Religion is wholly grounded vpon the Popes fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and fantaſticall Decretals.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Booke and Chapter he ſheweth, that true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion doth tye vs to <hi>one God, that is Almightie.</hi> But Popiſh Religion doth oblige men to ſerue Saints and Angels, and to worſhip many Gods on euery Altar, that haue no power. And againe, <hi>Non ſit nobis Religio humanorum operum cultus.</hi> And afterward, <hi>Non ſit nobis Religio cultus hominum mortuorum.</hi> And ſpeaking of Angels, he ſayth, <hi>Honoramus eos charitate non ſeruitute nec eis Templa conſtruimus.</hi> So he declareth, that Religion conſiſteth not in the worſhip of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or the workes of mens hands, or in the worſhip of dead men, or Saints, or in the ſeruice of Angels; ſhewing, that then Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were not built in the honor of Angels, or any Seruice giuen to them: all direct contrarie to the practiſe of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In ijs quae aperte in Scripturis poſita ſunt inueniuntur illa omnia quae continent fidem moreſque viuendi,</hi> ſayth hee, <hi>lib. 3. de Doctr. Chriſt. c. 9.</hi> So hee holdeth Scriptures to be <hi>both ſufficient</hi> and perſpicuous in all matters concerning ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. And <hi>Lib. de Bon. Viduit. c. 1. Sancta Scriptura noſtrae Doctrinae regulam figit, ne audeamus ſupera plus quam oportet.</hi> All contrarie to the Doctrine of falſe <hi>Romiſh</hi> Catholikes, which hold the Scriptures to be obſcure and darke, imperfect, and no ſufficient Rule, without Traditions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diſp. 2. contr. Fortunat. After that man ſinned by Free-will, wee were caſt headlong into a neceſſitie of ſinning.</hi> And <hi>Enchirid. ad Laurent. c. 30. Man, ill vſing Free-will, loſt both himſelfe and it.</hi> But falſe Catholikes denie that it is ſo loſt, but that we may freely doe well.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lib. 4. contr. Iulian.</hi> he denyeth, that Infidels can doe works pleaſing to God: which Papiſts admit not.</p>
            <p>In his Booke <hi>de Vnit. Eccleſ. c. 1.</hi> he acknowledgeth <hi>no Head of the Church but CHRIST IESVS, the onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:238:6"/>Sonne of the liuing God, who is alſo the Sauior of his Body.</hi> Falſe Catholikes make the Pope to be the Head of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnes homines ſub Lege conſtitutos reos facit Lex,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine.</hi> But falſe Papiſts ſeeke for iustification by the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuſtitia noſtra quamvis vera ſit, tamen tanta eſt in hac vita, vt potius peccatorum remiſſione conſtet, quam perfectione virtutum,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auguſtine, lib. 19. de Ciuit. Dei, c. 27.</hi> He ſayth, <hi>Our iuſtice ſtandeth in remiſſion or ſinnes,</hi> and <hi>not in the perfection of vertue:</hi> The Papiſts teach contrarie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lib. 2. contr. Epiſt. Parmen. c. 8.</hi> he denyeth, that S. <hi>Paul,</hi> or other Apoſtles, are our Mediators. And againe, <hi>Pro quo nullus interpellat ſed ipſo pro omnibus hic vnus veruſque Mediator eſt.</hi> But this Apoſtate, and his Conſorts, vſe the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> of Angels, and Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum</hi> Petro <hi>dicitur ad omnes dicitur, paſce Oues meus,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine, de Agon. Chriſt. c. 30.</hi> Papiſts contrarie beleeue, that theſe words doe properly belong to <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Pope.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When it was ſayd to</hi> Peter, <hi>I will giue thee the Keyes of the Kingdome of Heauen, the Church Vniuerſall was ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine, Tract. 124. in loan.</hi> The Apoſtate contrarie reſtraineth this to the Pope.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> in <hi>Epiſt. ad lanuar. 118. &amp; Lib. 3. de Doctr. Chriſt. c. 9.</hi> mentioneth onely two Sacraments, which our Church alloweth: Falſe Catholikes adde other fiue, and hold, they iuſtifie <hi>ex opere operato;</hi> which was a Doctrine neuer knowne by S. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lib. de Fid. ad Petrum, c. 19.</hi> he ſayth, <hi>The Church cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to offer the Sacrifice of Bread and Wine, wherein there is action of Graces, and a commemoration of Chriſts Fleſh, which he gaue for vs, and of his Bloud, which he ſhed for vs.</hi> Contrariwiſe, the Apoſtate and his fellowes denie, that Bread and Wine are effered, and ſuppoſe, that his Fleſh and Bloud is really offered for vs in the Euchariſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:238:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Tract. 30. in Ioan.</hi> S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſayth, that Chriſts Body, in which he roſe againe, muſt be in one place. And <hi>Serm. 53. de Verb. Dom. Chriſtus caput noſtrum ſurſum in coelis eſt.</hi> The Aduerſaeries of Truth ſay he is here below on euerie Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and beleeue, that the Pope is the Head of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tractat. 26. in Ioan. &amp; in Pſal. 77.</hi> he ſayth, that <hi>the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of the Old and New Teſtament are equall in the thing that is ſignified, though diuers in ſignes:</hi> Which ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth the carnall reaell preſence of Chriſts Body and Bloud, vnder the accidents of Bread and Wine, in the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>De morib. Eccleſ. Cath. lib. 1. c. 3.</hi> S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſuch as <hi>worſhip Sepulchres and Pictures. Et de Fid. &amp; Symb. c. 7. Tale ſimulachrum Deo nefas eſt Chriſtiano in Templo collorari,</hi> ſayth he, condemning the making of the Image of God, and placing it in Churches. In his Booke <hi>de Haereſ.</hi> he ſheweth, that the <hi>Simonians</hi> &amp; <hi>Carpocratians</hi> were reputed Heretikes: yet the worſhip of Images and Saints Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques is reputed no ſmall part of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faith.</p>
            <p>In his <hi>6.</hi> Booke of <hi>Confeſſions, c. 5.</hi> hee ſheweth, that God perſwadeth vs to beleeue Scriptures, condemning ſuch as aske, how wee know that <hi>the Scriptures were deliuered to men by the miniſtration of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> But falſe and counterfeit Chriſtians, and this Apoſtate, doe make this queſtion commonly, and beleeue not Scriptures, without Tradition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid mihi eſt cum hominibus vt ipſi confeſſiones meas audiant,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine, lib. 10. Confeſſ. c. 2.</hi> But the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and his Apoſtaticall Conſorts thinke it a matter neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to confeſſe, and reckon vp all ſinnes, and the circumstances thereof, making Confeſſion a neceſſarie ingredient of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Penance.</p>
            <p>Finally, it were an eaſie matter to ſhew, that S. <hi>AVGV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STINE</hi> doth diſcord with the Papiſts in all thoſe Points wherein they differ from vs; but this may ſerue for a taſſe in the interim, vntill we diſcourſe hereof more particularly in the ſecond Chapter of the Treatiſe following. Now this is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, to ſhew the falſitie and pouertie of the Tranſlator, and
<pb facs="tcp:238:7"/>his Notes and Obſernations vpon S. <hi>AVSTINES Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions,</hi> wherein moſt ſimply and weakely hee endeuoureth to make that worthie Father of his partie. <hi>Quid eſt egere,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>AVSTINE, de Vit. Beat.</hi> And he anſwereth, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiam non habere.</hi> And againe he ſayth. <hi>Nihil eſt aliud habere egeſtatem quam habere ſtultitiam.</hi> So that by Saint <hi>AVSTINES</hi> iudgement, this man being void of Wiſdome, and full of Foolerie, is but a poore Tranſlator, wracking him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vpon S. <hi>AVSTINE,</hi> vpon whom he meant to lay the ground of his fooliſh and vaine Religion. Therein alſo we may percciue how vainely our Aduerſaries boaſt of Fathers, and eſpecially of S. <hi>AVGVSTINE,</hi> who in all important mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith are directly oppoſite vnto them. But lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all further preambular ſpeeches, we will now begin to handle ſuch matters, as the rinegned Tranſlator doth principaelly inſiſt vpon.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:238:7"/>
            <head>THE VNMASKING <hi>of a Maſſe-monger.</hi> WHO In the counterfeit habit of S. AVGVSTINE hath cunningly crept into the Cloſets of many <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ladyes: <hi>OR, The Vindication of S.</hi> AVGVSTINES <hi>Confeſsions,</hi> from the falſe and malicious Calumniations of a late noted Apoſtate.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> That S. <hi>AVSTINE</hi> neuer knew either the Decrees of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticle of <hi>Trent</hi> enacted against vs, or that part of the Romiſh Religion, which the Church of <hi>England</hi> admitteth not, and which the Apoſtate and his conſorts hold to bee Catholicke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Vch doe our Aduerſaries inſiſt vpon the name of <hi>Catholikes</hi> and title of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church.</hi> So doe alſo all other He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, as ſaith <hi>Lactantius, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Diuin. inſtit. c</hi> 30. <hi>Singuli qui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> haeriticorum cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, ſe potiſſimum Chriſtianos &amp; ſuam eſſe eccleſiam eatholicam putant.</hi> But if that be Catholike which at all times, of all Chriſtians and in all
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:238:8"/>places hath beene holden as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>incentius Lirinenſis aduerſ. hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</hi> teacheth vs, then certes the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not Catholike.</p>
               <p>In the judgement of S <hi>Auguſtine</hi> it cannot be accompted either Catholike or ſoundly Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>For firſt S. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>Auſtine</hi> referreth himſelfe in all matters of faith to holy Scriptures, and ſpeaketh moſt reuerently of them, <hi>Canonica ſcriptura veteris &amp; noui Teſtamenti,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Lib.</hi> 11. <hi>contr. Fauſt. c.</hi> 5. <hi>Est in ſede quadum ſublimiter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituta, cujus authoritati ſeruiat omnis fidelis &amp; pius intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus.</hi> Hee placeth their Authoritie aboue all Councels, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Popes, and would haue all pious Chriſtians to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their vnderſtanding vnto them; but ſuch as rayled vpon them, and called them a dead and killing letter, and ſaid they were imperfect, obſcure, ambiguous, and flexible, he neuer did acknowledge to be Catholikes or Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>He neuer beleeued nor knew the traditions of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> concerning the conſecrating of Croſſes and Images, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> their greaſing and croſſing of Altars, their-hallowing of Churches with oyle, holy-water and aſhes, their conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of paſchall Lambes, Salt, Holy-water, Aſhes, the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing of Bells, the bleſſing of Prieſts garments, the myſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Maſſe, their ſhauing and greaſing vſed in giuing Orders, nor the reſt of their traditions.</p>
               <p>He beleeued not that traditions not written were to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with like affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> as we receiue holy Scriptures. Nay contrary, he gaue the higheſt place to Canonicall Scripture.</p>
               <p>That traditions ſhould be added to the rule of Faith was more then he could euer imagine. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>Sancta ſcriptura,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Debon. viduit. c.</hi> 1. <hi>Noſtrae doctrinae regulam figit.</hi> Holy <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture giueth vs a fixt and certaine rule.</hi> And <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>con. Donatist.</hi> He accounteth the Scriptures to be <hi>a diuine</hi> ballancer, <hi>wherein Doctrines may be juſtly weighed.</hi> But other ballancers he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteth <hi>deceitfull. Non afferamus ſtateras doloſas,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Vb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> appendamus quod volumus, &amp; quomodo volumus pro arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie noſtro; dicentes hoc graue, hoc leue, ſed afferamus diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:238:8"/>ſtateram de Scripturis ſanstis, tanquam de the ſauris Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicis, &amp; in illa quid ſit grauius appendamus: imò non appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus, ſid à Domino appenſam recognoſcamus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> beleeueth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> that the old vulgar Latine tranſlation of the Bible is authenticall, and neither the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew text of the old, nor the Greeke of the new Teſtament. But S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> gaue no ſuch credit to that, or any other tranflation. Nay contrary, <hi>lib.</hi> 15. <hi>de ciuit. D.c.</hi> 13. hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth Originals before all Tranſlations. <hi>Ei linguae potius credatur,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>vnde est in aliam per interpretes facta tranſlatio.</hi> And <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de doctr. Chriſt. c.</hi> 11. He would haue men <hi>to haue recourſe to the Hebrew and Greeke text, for the variety of Tranſlations. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de doctr. Chriſt c.</hi> 15. he ſaith, Tranſlations ought to giue place to the Greeke text of the New Teſtament.</p>
               <p>To come to the Pope who is the founder of the grand I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll of the Maſſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> and the Oracle from whom his followers deriue the certainty of their Romiſh traditions, S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> neuer knew the man. Nay, if any man in his time had ſaid, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had two Swords and power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Kings and diſpoſe of their Kingdomes, and that he was the Vniuerſall Biſhop of the Church, the head, foundation and Spouſe miniſteriall of the ſame, and finally that hee was the ſupreame judge of Faith, and had Authoritie to make new Articles of the Faith; doth any man thinke, that ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wiſe a man could haue contained himſelfe within the limites of patience, hearing ſuch monſtrous Paradoxes?</p>
               <p>The Schoole doctrine concerning Merites of congruitie and condignitie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Iuſtice by workes, bodies being in many places at once, and filling no place, accidents nouriſhing like ſubſtances, and yet ſubſiding without any ſubiect, Popiſh diſpenſations for all flagitious ſinnes, Diuels tormenting juſt mens ſoules in Purgatory, ſatisfactions for ſinne by Whipping and going Bare-foot, waſhing away ſinnes with Holy-water, and expiating them by knocking the breſt, and the Prieſts bleſſing, and ſuch other Schoole-points, were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:238:9"/>not knowne to S. <hi>Austine,</hi> nor heard of in his time.</p>
               <p>All the authenticall Doctrine of the Romiſh Synagogue is contayned in the Popes decretals and decrees, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> and was publiſhed and confirmed in the ſecond <hi>Nicene</hi> Synode, in the aſſemblies of <hi>Laterane, Conſtance, Florence,</hi> and <hi>Trent.</hi> How then could that holy Father know a Faith, that was ſo long after his time eſtabliſhed? Could he Prophecie that the men of <hi>Trent</hi> would decree that Chriſtians ſhould be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Popes law? That the Images of the Trinitie ſhould bee worſhipped with <hi>Latria?</hi> That Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſhould be inuocated? That men ſhould beleeue Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, auricular Confeſſion, ſeauen Sacraments, and ſuch like late doctrines?</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Austine,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 
                  <hi>lib</hi> 11. <hi>contr. Fauſt. c.</hi> 5. Would haue all <hi>pious vnderſtanding made ſubiect to the high authority of Scriptures.</hi> Neither did he beleeue, that the ſame might be confirmed by any mans writing. Is it then likely, that he ſhould teach or thinke, that Scriptures in reſpect of vs receiued their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from the Churches of <hi>Romes</hi> decrees or from the Pope?</p>
               <p>That the Pope ſhould bee an infallible Interpretor of Scripture, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> and ſupreame Moderator of Religion, S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> neuer heard. Nay, diſaduowing all the Popes decretals and other mens writings, he ſignifieth, that <hi>hee oweth his conſent without all exception, onely to canonicall Scriptures. In quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumlibet hominum ſcriptis,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>lib. de natur. &amp; grat. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſum quia ſolis canonicis ſcripturis debeo ſine vlla recuſatione conſenſum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
                  <hi>Auſtine</hi> neuer prayed to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> nor call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her and other Saints and Angels, or teach that they were to be worſhipped with <hi>Dulia.</hi> If he had dedicated his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> as doth the Apoſtate his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd tranſlation, I ſhould beleeue, that he had learned ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what from that holy Father.</p>
               <p>He neuer beleeued that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was conceiued without ſinne, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> or that ſhe was the mediatrix or redemptrix
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:238:9"/>of Mankind together with her Sonne, or that her body is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready aſſumed into heauen, as this Apoſtate her deuout ſlaue and others hold.</p>
               <p>Nor did hee euer teach, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> that Saints in heauen heard the prayers and vnderſtood the thoughts of all men, and in all places here on earth, or that they could helpe them, giue them grace, and deliuer them.</p>
               <p>Hee might make a commemoration of the names of the faithfull hence departed, and commend his Mother to God. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> But neuer taught or beleeued, that his mothers and other faithfull mens ſoules which he mentioned at the Lords table were tormented in Purgatory.</p>
               <p>Hee was no Maſſe-prieſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> nor euer offered Chriſts body really for quicke and dead; nor ſaid Maſſe for ſicke horſes as Maſſe Prieſts doe.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Chriſts</hi> body and blood ſhould bee contained vnder the accidents of Bread and Wine, and that ſeuerally, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> is ſo extrauagant a Paradoxe, that it could neuer be found in the holy Fathers writings. Nor could he beleeue, that either reprobates or brute beaſts did eat <hi>Chriſts</hi> fleſh and drinke his blood.</p>
               <p>The Sacrament hee neither adored, nor carried it about, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> nor put it into a Pixe, neither did he allow any ſuch thing done by others.</p>
               <p>He neuer confeſſed his ſinnes to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> or to Angels or Saints, or pray them to intercede for him, as doe Maſſe-Prieſts.</p>
               <p>Much leſſe did hee pray for <hi>Chriſts</hi> body, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> that it might bee graciouſly accepted, as was the <hi>Sacrifice of</hi> Abell <hi>and</hi> Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech, and carried into heauen, as doe the Apoſtates conſorts.</p>
               <p>This Apoſtate cannot demonſtrate, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> that St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> euer thought, that Salt and Water conſecrated <hi>would cauſe Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ceaſe, and driue away Diuels.</hi> Let him bring forth the teſtimony of any man or Diuell to proue this, and then his deuoted followers may perchance beleeue him.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:238:10"/>
               <p>That Chriſtians ſhould be burned, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> for holding that fleſh may be eaten on Frydayes, or Saints Vigils, as this vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Apoſtate and his Teachers beleeue, he cannot prooue that ſo holy a Father as S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> eyther taught or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</p>
               <p>The Precepts of the Romiſh Church, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> concerning Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, Faſts, Maſſes, auricular Confeſſion, and prohibition of Marriage, were neuer knowne to S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> nor could be, being brought in by diuers Popes that liued ſince his time.</p>
               <p>Neyther did he teach or beleeue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> that Treaſons againſt Princes and States, heard by Prieſts in Confeſſion, were not to be reuealed; or that the ſeale of Confeſſion of which the Maſſe-Prieſts talke as of a diuine Myſterie, was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by God.</p>
               <p>Of the caſes reſerued to the Pope, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> which are a principall bulwarke of the Papall authoritie, S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> neuer heard newes.</p>
               <p>Neyther was hee acquainted with the Popes Penitenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie Taxe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> or the rules of his Chancerie; nor thought it fit, that Periurie, Inceſt, Murder, and all irregularities, ſhould bediſpenſed withall, or pardoned for Money.</p>
               <p>Finally, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> all thoſe Hereſies and Nouelties which the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts now hold and maintaine with all ſraud and force, were eyther reiected by S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> or vtterly vnknowne vnto him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> That thoſe principall points of Romiſh Religion which we reiect, are alſo reiected and contradicted by S. <hi>AVSTINE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NEyther doth S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> onely paſſe ouer in ſilence the new-forged Religion of Papiſts, maintained by this Apoſtate, but alſo directly oppugne the ſame. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> They euery where vilifie holy Scriptures, as <hi>imperfect, difficult, ambiguous,</hi> calling them a <hi>Noſe of Wax,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:238:10"/>a <hi>Delphian Sword, a dead Letter, Matter of Contention.</hi> S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> contrariwiſe extolleth them, as placed in a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime place of authoritie, and from them <hi>he would haue none to depart. Extat authoritas ſacrae Scripturae, vnde mens noſtra deuiare non debet,</hi> ſaith he <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Trinit. cap.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>They admit Traditions and the Popes Definitions for a Rule of Faith: but this holy Father admitteth no Rule, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> but holy Scripture. <hi>Canon Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>conſtitutus eſt. ad quem certi Apoſtolorum &amp; Prophetarum libri pertinent.</hi> The words are extant, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>contr. creſc. gram. c.</hi> 31.</p>
               <p>In the ſame place he would not haue any to iudge of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> but to iudge according to it: but the Pope taketh vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to taxe and iudge of Scripture, yea, to pronounce without it, and againſt it.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtate and his Conſorts eſteeme the Scriptures to be hard and ambiguous.S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Doct. Chriſt. c.</hi> 9. ſaith, <hi>That whatſoeuer is neceſſarie to ſaeluation, is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in plaine places of Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ieſuits</hi> muſter againſt vs, Traditions, Decretals, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and ſuch like teſtimonies: but S. <hi>Austine</hi> reiecting all the reſt, would haue all proofes deriued out of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>Lib. de vnit. Eccleſ. c.</hi> 3. <hi>Auferantur,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ille de medio quae aduerſus nos inuicem, non ex Diuims Canonicis Libris, ſed aliunde recitamus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They goe about to marke out a Church by Vnitie, Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſalitie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Antiquitie, and Succeſſion: but S. <hi>Auſtine de vnit. Eccleſ. c.</hi> 1. would haue the queſtion of the Church to be decided by Scriptures. <hi>Inter nos &amp; Donatiſtas quaeſtio eſt, vbi ſit Eccleſia, quid ergo facturi ſumus,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in verbis noſtris eam quaeſituri, an in verbis capitis ſui Domini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe preſumptuous fellowes preferre themſelues before Scripture, determining according to the Popes Decretals, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> what Bookes are Canonicall, and what the meaning is of euery Text: but S. <hi>Auſtine, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>contr. Creſc. c.</hi> 21. ſheweth, that neyther any <hi>particular man,</hi> nor <hi>the Church it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:238:11"/>ſelfe,</hi> is <hi>to preferre it ſelfe before Chriſt.</hi> Now who knoweth not, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeaketh to vs in Scriptures? <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>non debet ſe Chriſto praeponere.</hi> And <hi>Confeſſ.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 23. he would not <hi>haue any to iudge of the ſublime authoritie of the Booke of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They receiue not holy Scriptures, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> vnleſſe the Church, that is, the Pope, propoſe them and declare them to be Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. S. <hi>Auſtine, lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 5. blameth ſuch as are not by Scriptures perſwaded to accept them.</p>
               <p>They hold the old Latine vulgar Tranſlation to be au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> but contrarie to S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> iudgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 
                  <hi>Leo Caſtrius, Lindaue,</hi> and diuers other Papiſts, taxe holy Scriptures in the Originals, of <hi>Impuritie,</hi> and <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption:</hi> but contrarie to S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> iudgement, <hi>Ep.</hi> 108. and <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de doctr. Chriſt. c.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>The Bookes of <hi>Toby,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
                  <hi>Iudith, Wiſdome, Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> and the <hi>Machabees,</hi> the Papiſts receiue as Canonicall: but S. <hi>Auguſtine, Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>contr. Creſc. c.</hi> 31. placeth no Bookes in the Canon of the Old Teſtament, but ſuch as were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Prophets; of which number, theſe will hardly be proued to be.</p>
               <p>They make <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be our Mediator, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> according to his Humanitie onely; which is contrarie to S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, who in his Homily <hi>de Ouibus, c.</hi> 12. doth attribute this worke of Mediation to his Perſon in both Natures. <hi>Diuina humanitas,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>&amp; humana Diuinitas Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The worſhip and inuocation of holy men departed, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> are a great part of the Romiſh Religion: but S. <hi>Auſtine de ver. Relig. c. vlt.</hi> forbiddeth vs to place Religion in Reliques, and the inuocation of dead men. <hi>Non ſit nobis Religio,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>culius hominum mortuorum.</hi> And <hi>Lib.</hi> 22. <hi>de Ciuit. Dei, c.</hi> 10. he ſaith: <hi>Chriſtians departed, are named at the Altar, but not called vpon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auguſtine de Morib. Eccl. Cath. c.</hi> 34. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> ſaith hee knew <hi>ſome</hi> that worſhipped <hi>dead mens Tombes,</hi> and <hi>Pictures;</hi> but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:238:11"/>ſuch are condemned by him. In his Booke <hi>de Haereſib.</hi> hee condemneth it as an Hereſie of the <hi>Simonians</hi> and <hi>Carpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratians,</hi> that they worſhipped Images, and burnt incenſe vnto them: Yet doth not the Apoſtate, nor his Apoſtaticall mates, forbeare to worſhip Reliques of Saints and Images, and to burne incenſe vnto them.</p>
               <p>Hee acknowledged but two Sacraments, properly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> which, as he ſpeaketh, flowed out of Chriſts ſide: He ſoecifieth alſo two Sacraments in his 118. <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> viz. <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and the Lords Supper; Manauit ſanguis &amp; aqua Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae gemina Sacramenta,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Symb. c.</hi> 6. But the Apoſtate not regarding S. <hi>Austines</hi> authoritie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth fiue Sacraments beſide theſe two.</p>
               <p>He ſaith: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſible Sacraments,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> 
                  <hi>without the ſanctification of inuiſible grace, profit nothing;</hi> as we reade in <hi>Quaest. ſuper Leuit. Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 84. But the Apoſtate and his Conſorts beleeue, that viſible Sacraments conferre grace <hi>ex opere operato.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> calleth the Sacrament <hi>a figure of Chriſts Bodie;</hi> and <hi>Lib. contr. Adimantum, c.</hi> 12. <hi>Christ,</hi> as he writeth, <hi>doubted not to ſay, This is my Bodie, when he gaue a ſigne of his Bodie:</hi> But Papiſts cannot brooke, that this Sacrament ſhould be called a ſigne, or a figure of Chriſts Bodie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take away the ſpaces of places from Bodies</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> 
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 57. <hi>ad Dardanum</hi>) <hi>and they will be no where; and becauſe they are no where, they will not be at all: Spatia loco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tolle corporibus, nuſquam erunt, &amp; quia nuſquam erunt, non erunt.</hi> And in his 20. Booke <hi>contr. Faustum,</hi> he faith; <hi>Chriſt, according to his corporall preſence, could not be at one time in the Sunne and Moone, and on the Croſſe.</hi> And in his 30. Treatiſe on <hi>Joan.</hi> he ſaith; <hi>The Bodie of Christ must be in one place.</hi> But this rinegate, Apoſtating as well from S. <hi>Auſtiue,</hi> as from the Chriſtian Faith, holdeth that <hi>Christs</hi> true Bodie is in euery Altar, and diuers Countries, at one inſtant, and yet filleth no place.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:238:12"/>
               <p>It is againſt Pietie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> as hee is alledged, <hi>c. vtrum, Diſt.</hi> 2. <hi>de Conſecrat.</hi> to thinke, that <hi>Chriſts</hi> Bodie is deuoured with teeth; <hi>Chriſtum vorari dentibus fas non eſt.</hi> He faith alſo, that <hi>his fleſh is no meat for mens teeth, but for their ſoules, Tract.</hi> 25. <hi>in Ioan.</hi> But this impietie, of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring and eating <hi>Chriſt</hi> with teeth, and with the mouth, is part of the Apoſtates impious Religion.</p>
               <p>He ſaith alſo, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> 
                  <hi>The wicked which accord not with Chriſt, doe not eat Chriſts Bodie, or drinke his Bloud,</hi> as is alledged, <hi>c. qui diſcordat, Diſt.</hi> 2. <hi>de Conſecr.</hi> Yet this fellow rineguing from S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Doctrine, holdeth, that not only the wicked, but alſo brute beaſts eating the Sacrament, both eat his Bodie, and drinke his Bloud.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Simul ſumimus,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> 
                  <hi>ſimul bibimus, quia ſimul viuimus; Wee doe take the Sacrament, and drinke together, becauſe wee liue together,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in <hi>Serm. ad Neoplaſt.</hi> which is alledged, <hi>c. quia paſſus, Diſt.</hi> 2. <hi>de Conſecrat.</hi> And can the rinegate in his rinegued Conſcience beleeue, that S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> allowed priuate Maſſes and halfe Communions?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Free-will being captiuated</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine contr.</hi> 2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> 
                  <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. Pelag. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 8.) <hi>is of no ſtrength, but to ſinne: Liberum arbitrium captiuatum non niſi ad peccandum valet.</hi> And will this captiuated ſlaue of Antichriſt contradict ſuch a holy Father, and ſay, that Free-will is not captiuated, but hath power to doe well?</p>
               <p>The ſame Father, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> 
                  <hi>de Nupt. &amp; Concupiſc. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; contr. Julian. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; de Ciuit. Dei. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>&amp; in Pſal.</hi> 31. <hi>in Praefat.</hi> teacheth, that Infidels ſinne in all their workes: but the rinegate and his Mates will not ſubmit themſelues to S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> iudgement; nor denie, but that Infidels may doe good workes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Church</hi> (as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaith, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> 
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>contr. Donatiſt. c.</hi> 27.) <hi>conſiſteth of iuſt and holy men:</hi> and in his Expoſition on the 56. <hi>Pſal.</hi> hee ſaith it conſiſteth of <hi>all the faithfull, that are the members of Chriſt.</hi> And will the Apoſtate hold, that wicked Popes, Cardinals, Maſſe-Prieſts, Monkes and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:238:12"/>Fryars, whereof ſome are Infidels, are the true members of Chriſts Body. His Maſter <hi>Bellarmine, de Eccleſ. c.</hi> 2. ſaith, a man may be a true member of the Church, if he commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate outwardly in Faith and Sacraments with the Church, and be ſubiect to the Pope, albeit he haue neyther inward Faith, nor Vertue. But who will not rather beleeue S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> then theſe two Pſeudo-Catholikes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sine bonorum operum meritis per fidem iustificaetur impius,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> ſaith S. <hi>Austine</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67. Yet this rinegat doubteth not, but as he hath the ſinnes of his youth, and ſcabs inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, ſo he is iuſtified by charitie inherent, and good works, if he haue any.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Austine</hi> in his Commentaries, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely condemne mens Merits, <hi>esteeming all our ſufferings vile, and not worthie of that which we receiue.</hi> And in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83. <hi>Quicquid promiſit, indignis promiſit: Whatſoeuer God promiſed,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>he promiſed to men vnworthie, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward might be not of Workes, but of Grace.</hi> Afterward hee ſaith, <hi>Our iustice is not of Merites of men, but of Gods gift.</hi> And yet this vnworthie fellow, and his thrice-vnworthie Mates, boaſt continually of their worth, and teach mens Merites.</p>
               <p>The ſame holy Father alſo, <hi>Confeſſ. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 42. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all reconciliation to God, made by Angels; and in his Booke <hi>de Haereſib.</hi> condemneth ſuch for Heretikes, as pray to Angels. How then can ſuch rinegates reconcile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to S. <hi>Austine,</hi> praying to Angels, and truſting to be reconciled by Angels, and holpen by their interceſſion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib. de Haereſ. c.</hi> 88. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> hee condemneth <hi>Pelagius</hi> for an Heretike, holding that man may by free-will diſpoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to grace; and that iuſt men can liue without ſinne, and be ſaued by their owne ſtrength. The which Fancies being embraced by this Heretike; who ſeeth not, that he concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth rather with <hi>Pelagius,</hi> then holdeth with S. <hi>Auſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Heracleonites</hi> vſed to giue Extreme Vnction to their followers, mumbling certaine prayers ouer them, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> in a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:238:13"/>Tongue not vnderſtood: But for this, S <hi>Austine</hi> ſheweth they were condemned as Heretikes, <hi>de Haereſ. c.</hi> 16. Doth the Apoſtate then thinke S. <hi>Austine</hi> is of his partie who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth Extreme Vnction, and the barbarous miniſtring of it in a Tongue not vnderſtood?</p>
               <p>Like wiſe commending bare-footed Fryars and Nunnes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> and eſteeming their worke in ſo going, meritorious; is hee not rather to be condemned among the nudipedale Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, ſo eſteemed by S. <hi>Auſtine, de Haereſ.</hi> 68. then reputed a Diſciple of that holy Father?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vae etiam laudabili vitae hominum,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> 
                  <hi>ſi remota miſericordia diſcutias eam,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Austine, Lib. Confeſſ.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 13. Yet this Apoſtate and his glorious Companions ſtanding on their Merites, thinke they need not Gods mercie, in meriting Heauen.</p>
               <p>They talke alſo of the Bleſſed Virgins Conception with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out originall ſinne: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> but S. <hi>Austine</hi> held, that originall ſinne paſſed ouer all, and would not free her from this origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall corruption.</p>
               <p>Finally, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/> the whole Booke of S. <hi>Austines</hi> Confeſſions, and the forme and frame of it, doth plainely conuince this Apoſtate and his fellowes to be of a diuers Religion from S. <hi>Augustine.</hi> Hee dedicated no Booke to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> as doth this Apoſtate. Hee confeſſed his ſinnes to God onely; they, to Angels, Saints, and the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> Hee called vpon God onely, and not vpon Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> Theſe pray more to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> to Angels and Saints, then to God. Hee eſteemed, that <hi>Christ</hi> was our onely Mediator; theſe flye to the mediation of Angels and Saints. Hee called vpon God, his Father; they, vpon the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> that is not ſo much as their Mother. Hee held the Vnitie of the Catholike Church; theſe are onely called Catholikes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing departed from the Catholike and Apoſtolike Faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:238:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> That the Apoſtate and his conſorts holding what the Church of <hi>England</hi> rejecteth are neither Catholikes nor hold the Cathoſike Faith.</head>
               <p>IN this Booke in his Preface and notes, and all his idle talke, the Hereticall rinegate preſumeth to arrogate to himſelfe and his fellowes the name and title of <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes.</hi> And that is the ſcope of his Preface, and the end of his Tranſlation, to iuſtifie himſelfe, and the Faith of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church to bee all <hi>Catholike,</hi> a matter ſo impudently preſumed, and ſo falſely affirmed, as nothing more.</p>
               <p>For firſt, <hi>None are Catholikes, but ſuch as hold that Faith,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>that is truly Catholike and Apoſtolike.</hi> But the Faith of this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate &amp; his fellowes is neither. They belieue the Popes De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretals, and the doctrine of <hi>Trent</hi> publiſhed againſt the true Faith, which neither the Apoſtles taught, nor ancient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes euer beleeued; nay, it is not receiued by all Papiſts.</p>
               <p>No Heretikes can be reputed Catholikes. S. <hi>Austine,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>de ver. Relig. c.</hi> 8. ſaith, <hi>They are without the Church.</hi> And in the end of his <hi>Tract. de hereſib.</hi> hee ſaith, <hi>Haereſes qui tenuerit Chriſtianus catholicus non eſt:</hi> but Papiſts holding the Popes particular ſect, and ſubmitting themſelues to his command are directly Heretikes. For firſt, they hold diuers Doctrines contrary to canonicall Scriptures, which are generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of all Catholikes: which <hi>Robert Groſthead</hi> in <hi>Heur.</hi> 3. <hi>apud Matth. Paris, Durand,</hi> and diuers others hold to bee hereſie. 2. They commonly interpret Scriptures contrary to the meaning of the Holy Ghoſt: which <hi>Hierome</hi> in his Commentaries vpon S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians</hi> hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to be hereſie. Now that they interpret Scriptures con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the meaning of the Holy Ghoſt, it appeareth by the <hi>Cap. ſolitae. de major. &amp; obed.</hi> and <hi>Vnam Sanctam, extr. com. de major. &amp; obed.</hi> and infinite other decretale Epiſtles, by the decrees of <hi>Trent,</hi> and Schoole diſputes. 3. With the <hi>Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niaens,</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:238:14"/>and <hi>Carpocratians,</hi> and <hi>Valentinians,</hi> they worſhip Images, and burne incenſe to them. 4. With the <hi>Angelickes</hi> and <hi>Caians,</hi> they worſhip Angels, and call vpon them. 5. With the <hi>Collyridians,</hi> they adore the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and offer conſecrated Hoaſts, or Cakes, in her honour. 6. With the <hi>Marcionites,</hi> and <hi>Manichees,</hi> they deſtroy <hi>Chriſts</hi> humane nature, giuing him a phantaſticall Bodie in the Sacrament. 7. With the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> they make mans free-will the cauſe of mans predeſtination, and ſaluation; and hold, that man is able to prepare himſelfe to grace, and with grace to liue without ſinne. 8. With the <hi>Cathariſts,</hi> they beleeue their workes are cleare without ſinne, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly iuſt. 9. With the <hi>Audeans,</hi> and <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> they teach, <hi>that their Prieſts forgiue ſinnes.</hi> 10. With the <hi>Stau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolatrians,</hi> they worſhip the Croſſe. 11. With <hi>Capernaites</hi> they beleeue, that <hi>Chriſts</hi> fleſh is eaten with the mouth. Finally, with the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> they beleeue the iuſtice of Workes.</p>
               <p>Chriſt giuing his Apoſtles commiſſion to goe forth into the World, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> bad them teach all Nations whatſoeuer he had commanded them. But neyther did the Apoſtles teach, nor was it our Sauiours meaning, that all Nations ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue and obſerue the Doctrine of <hi>Trent,</hi> the determination of Schooles, and the Popes Decretals, concerning the bodily Reall preſence of Chriſt, vnder the accidents of Bread and Wine, in the Sacrament; Tranſubſtantiation, and Auricular Confeſſion, the inuocation of Saints and Angels, the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Croſſe, of the Images of the Trinitie, and the Sacrament, the adoration of Reliques, the conſecration of holy Water, of <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> and Paſchall Lambes, and ſuch like Romiſh Traditions.</p>
               <p>All true Catholikes profeſſe one Catholike and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Faith: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> how then can the Apoſtate and his Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Popes Diſciples, challenge to themſelues the name of Catholikes, beleeuing the traditions of men to be the Word of God, and receiuing the Doctrine of <hi>Trent,</hi> and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:238:14"/>Schoole-ſophiſters concerning Purgatory, Indulgences, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Maſſes, halfe Communions, Tranſubſtantion, and ſuch like, that is neither Catholike, Apoſtolike, nor Chriſtian?</p>
               <p>As we know an Artificers worke by the rule, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> ſo we know and diſcerne faithfull Chriſtians and Catholikes by holy Scriptures, which are the rule of Faith, who then can iuſtly eſteeme Papiſts to be Catholikes, that rayle vpon Scriptures and flye from them, and admit traditions and the Popes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretals, as the rule of their Faith? are Gods holy canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Scriptures no rule, without theſe additions?</p>
               <p>True Catholikes which are alſo the true members of <hi>Chriſts</hi> body adhere onely to <hi>Christ,</hi> as their head, ſpouſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> and moſt firme foundation of their Faith. But Popiſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes admit the Pope, as the head, ſpouſe and foundation of their ſuppoſed Catholike Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baſil in Epist.</hi> 80. <hi>ad Euſtat.</hi> and S. <hi>Auguſtine de nupt.</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                  <hi>&amp; concupiſc. c.</hi> 33. Would haue the canonicall Scriptures and <hi>Christ</hi> ſpeaking in them to iudge of a point of Chriſtian Doctrine. Thoſe therefore which contrary to theſe Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Fathers iudgement decline the iudgement of Scriptures and would haue the Pope to be ſupreame iudge in matters of Faith cannot be Catholikes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Creed ſetting forth that Faith, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> which he iudged, and all good Chriſtians receiue as Catholike, did not ſo much as in one word touch the Doctrine of <hi>Trent</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Traditions, Iuſtice of workes, Freewill diſpoſitions, 7. Sacraments, worſhipping of Saints and Images, and other hereſies reiected by vs. How then can Papiſts pretend, that their Religion is Catholike, which that Catholike Father admitted not as catholike?</p>
               <p>The Catholike Church euer prayed and adminiſtred Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments in a tongue vnderſtood of the hearers. The Friers, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Monkes and Maſſe-Prieſts therefore, that pray and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Sacraments in a tongue not vnderſtood of their hearers, declare themſelues and their adherents not to belong to the Catholike Church.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:238:15"/>
               <p>To hold, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath a body, that can neither bee felt nor ſeene, nor can it ſelfe either feele or ſee, is a Doctrine not of Catholikes, but of hereticall Papiſts, contrary to our Sauiours words, <hi>Luke</hi> 24. inuiting his Diſciples <hi>to feele and ſee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are alſo Heretikes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> and not Catholikes, that deſtroy <hi>Chriſts</hi> humane nature, and that giue him a body like a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. But ſo doth <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and his Diſciples the Papiſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Without mee,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> ſaith our Sauiour, <hi>you caen doe nothing,</hi> and this all true Catholikes beleeue. But the Apoſtate and his conſorts hold, that by force of Freewill they can turne to God and prepare themſelues to grace, and doe good.</p>
               <p>Catholikes thinke and ſpeake reuerently of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> But Papiſts blaſpheme and ſay his holy Body is eaten of brute beaſts, eating the Sacrament, and that it may be troden vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der feet, and caſt into vncleane places.</p>
               <p>Catholike Chriſtians neuer admitted 7. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Sacraments, or beleeued that men were iuſtified by Matrimony order, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, Confeſſion, or extreme Vnction. S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaid the Sacraments <hi>iſſued out of Chriſts ſide,</hi> which cannot bee veriſied of the fiue <hi>Romiſh</hi> new Sacraments.</p>
               <p>True Catholikes confeſſe their ſinnes to God, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> and ſo doth Scriptures and catholike Fathers teach them. Papiſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe confeſſe to Angels, Saints, and the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> They thinke themſelues alſo bound to confeſſe in the Prieſts care: contrary to the practice of true Catholikes.</p>
               <p>Catholikes doe beleeue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> that God onely doth forgiue ſinnes. Are they then Catholikes that teach, that Prieſts not onely intercede for ſinne, and declare ſinnes forgiuen, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo forgiue ſinnes, as did the <hi>Audean</hi> Heretikes mentioned by <hi>Theoderet, haeret. Fab. lib.</hi> 4?</p>
               <p>This Apoſtate and his mates beleeue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> that the Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> in body is aſſumed vp, and crowned <hi>Queene of Heauen;</hi> therefore they call vpon her as their Mediatrix. But this will not be proued to be a Catholike doctrine or practiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> Holy Martyrs and true Catholikes in time paſt ſuffered
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:238:15"/>death, becauſe they would not ſerue and worſhip Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and fall downe before dumbe Images. Are they then Catholikes, that worſhip Creatures, and adore Images?</p>
               <p>Not Catholikes, but the Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> and <hi>Cybele,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> vſed to lance, whip, and beat themſelues, thinking thereby to expiate ſinne. Are they then true Catholikes, that practiſe this Heatheniſh cuſtome, and commend it, as Chriſtian Diſcipline?</p>
               <p>Heathen men in time paſt fell downe and prayed before their Images; and can they pretend to be Chriſtian Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> that ſay <hi>Pater Noſter</hi> and <hi>Aue Maria</hi> before Stocks and Stones, practiſing this Heatheniſh cuſtome?</p>
               <p>Papiſts doe alſo fall downe before their Lord, and God, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> the Pope, kiſſing his foot: but this was neuer practiſed by ancient Catholikes, or true Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>True Chriſtians receiued deuoutly the holy Sacrament, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> and neyther put it into Pyxes, nor carryed it in Proceſſion. But theſe falſe Catholikes put it into Pyxes, carry it about on <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> day, and worſhip it as a God.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. accounteth it a Doctrine of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> to forbid Marriage, and to command Chriſtians to abſtaine from certaine Meats. Fooliſhly therefore Papiſts repute themſelues to be Catholikes, that forbid Marriage to Prieſts and Votaries, and reſtraine certaine Orders from eating Fleſh, and forbid all men to eate certaine Meates in Lent, and on Faſting-dayes.</p>
               <p>Catholike Chriſtians neuer beleeued they ſhould be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by eating Salt-Fiſh and Red Herrings, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> or forſwearing Marriage, or keeping Holy-dayes, and the Precepts of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> How then are Papiſts Catholikes, that beleeue ſuch fooleries?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jeſus, Maria,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> were neuer ioyned together in the Prayers of Catholikes; neyther did they prayſe <hi>Mary,</hi> as well as <hi>Jeſus.</hi> In this coniunction therefore, Papiſts make a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of themſelues from true Catholikes.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:238:16"/>
               <p>True Catholikes vſed alwayes in time paſt to burie the Bones and Reliques of Martyrs. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> A plaine argument, that ſuch as digge dead men out of their Graues, and worſhip them vpon Gods Altar, are Heretikes and Idolaters, and not Catholikes.</p>
               <p>Neyther did ancient Catholikes beleeue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> that an <hi>Agnus Dei</hi> was good againſt Lightening, and did as well purge ſinnes as Chriſts bloud: Which is another euidence, that Papiſts ſo beleeuing, are not Catholikes.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>John,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1. teacheth vs, that <hi>Chriſts bloud doth purge our ſinnes,</hi> and that is a point beleeued of all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes. Papiſts therefore, that beleeue that the bloud of Saints, and their owne bloud, and Satisfactions, yea, that holy Water doth purge ſinne, are but ſorry Catholikes.</p>
               <p>Sorry Catholikes alſo, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> and poore Chriſtians they are, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that the paines of ſinne are purged away in the fire of Purgatorie: For how are they purged, when they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed? And where did ancient Catholikes teach ſuch a Purgation?</p>
               <p>Farre alſo were Catholikes from beleeuing, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> that Salt and holy Water did driue away euill ſpirits.</p>
               <p>Ancient Chriſtian Catholikes did not ſay Maſſes for ſicke Horſes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> and Hogges; nor did they ſing Maſſes of the Crowne of Thornes, or of the three Nayles, or <hi>de praepu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Chriſti:</hi> nor had they ſeuerall Maſſes for Saylers, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Trauailers, Barren Women, Maides, and Women with Child. Are not Papiſts then degenerated quite from anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Catholike Religion?</p>
               <p>True Catholikes neuer bleſſed Croſſes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> nor beleeued that any Woodden or Stone Croſſe, conſecrated by them, was <hi>the Foundation of Faith,</hi> or <hi>a Defence in Aduerſitie,</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie againſt the Enemies,</hi> as Papiſts profeſſe in their Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificals, plainely declaring themſelues therein to be idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Heretikes.</p>
               <p>They doe alſo beleeue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/> that <hi>our Ladies Image can helpe ſuch as pray before it,</hi> and that <hi>it is a remedie againſt Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:238:16"/>and Lightening, inundation of Waters, and tumults of Warres;</hi> and that the Euangeliſt S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Image <hi>can expell Diuels, and bring to vs the aſsiſtance of Angels:</hi> matters ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heard of, or beleeued by Catholike Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>In a Booke called <hi>Antidot arium animae,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="34"/> ignorant Papiſts are taught to pray <hi>to the Image of Chriſts Face, called</hi> Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronica, <hi>to be purged from all blemiſhes of ſinne, to obtaine grace, and the fellowſhip of Saints.</hi> And this Prayer, as they ſay, was made by <hi>Iohn,</hi> the two and twentieth Pope of that name. But neyther can the Apoſtate, nor all his Maſters, the Ieſuites, prooue, that ſuch a Prayer was vſed by any ancient or true Chriſtian Catholike.</p>
               <p>Papiſts alſo are taught to conſecrate <hi>Bells,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="35"/> to cauſe <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts to ceaſe,</hi> and to <hi>driue away Diuels.</hi> They doe alſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute conſecrated Oyle, ſaying, <hi>Aue ſanctum Chriſma.</hi> But if the Apoſtate were all greaſed with <hi>Oyle,</hi> and ſigned with <hi>Croſſes,</hi> yet ſhall he neuer be able to ſhew, that this was a practiſe of true Catholikes.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. ſayth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/> 
                  <hi>Chriſt gaue the Church Apoſtles, Prophets, Euangeliſts, Paſtors, and Teachers;</hi> and true Catholikes beleeue, that theſe onely are ſufficient for <hi>the worke of the Miniſterie,</hi> and <hi>building of the Church.</hi> But the Papiſts, beſide theſe, haue in their Synagogue vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Popes, Cardinals, Inquiſitors, dumbe Woluiſh Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, that neyther feede nor worke any good, ſacrificing Prieſts, Monkes, Fryars, and Nunnes, which haue no inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution from Chriſt. How then are they Catholikes?</p>
               <p>Among Catholikes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/> none were choſen Biſhops in time paſt, but by the Clergie and People, nor conſecrated, but by conprouinciall Biſhops, as our Aduerſaries themſelues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, <hi>c. nulla ratio, Diſt.</hi> 62. and <hi>c. in nomine, Diſt.</hi> 23. And this was an Ordinance allowed alſo by <hi>Leo</hi> the firſt. But Popiſh Biſhops are intruded into their Seats by the Pope, without any allowance of the Clergie, or the People, or any conprouinciall Biſhops; and the Pope himſelfe is neyther elected by the Clergie, or People of <hi>Rome,</hi> but onely by a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:238:17"/>few Cardinals, the moſt part ſtrangers. And doe you call them Catholikes, that haue no Paſtors lawfully inſtituted by <hi>Christ,</hi> or called by the <hi>Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtles and their ſucceſſors were ſent by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to preach the Goſpell, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/> to baptize, and to adminiſter the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, according to <hi>Chriſts</hi> inſtitution; and thoſe are only true Catholikes, whole Prelates and Prieſts doe performe that Office which <hi>Chriſt</hi> enioyned them. But among Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Prieſts are ordained, not to preach, but to ſacrifice for quicke and dead: and Prelates are not ordered by the <hi>Church,</hi> but by <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> the Aduerſarie of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Church;</hi> and preach not the Goſpell, but humane Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Popes Decrees. Further, they obſerue not <hi>Chriſts</hi> inſtitution, in adminiſtring the Sacraments accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Chriſts</hi> inſtitution. How then are they true Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, among whom neyther the Word is truly preached, nor Sacraments are duly adminiſtred, and where in Doctrine and Chayre there is no Apoſtolicall ſucceſsion?</p>
               <p>Among ancient Catholikes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="39"/> onely the ſucceſſors of the Apoſtles preached, and baptized: but among Papiſts, Monkes and Fryars preach, albeit they be no ſucceſſors of the Apoſtles, nor inſtituted by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but by <hi>Antichrist;</hi> and Women ſometime are permitted to baptize, as if Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men could ſucceed the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith commeth by hearing,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/> 
                  <hi>and hearing by the Word of God,</hi> ſayth the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. and this Faith onely is the Catholike Chriſtian Faith. But among Papiſts, no Faith is allowed as good, but that which commeth from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the <hi>Church,</hi> as <hi>Caniſius</hi> teacheth, in <hi>Catech. c. de Fide.</hi> Now this <hi>Church</hi> is nothing but the Pope, and their Faith is grounded vpon Traditions not written, and the Decrees of the Pope. Can this Faith then be Catholike, and Diuine?</p>
               <p>Tiue Catholike Faith is alſo ioyned with firme Hope and aſſurance of faluation, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="41"/> together with the certaine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God and his will, and with feruent Charitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:238:17"/>God and our neighbour. But the Faith of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and his conſorts, is onely a bare aſſent to the word of God. Knowledge of God they haue little, contenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with an implicite Faith, and denying all aſſurance of ſaluation, and warring againſt all, that ſubmit not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the Pope, and his ſect. But ſuch a Faith is a dead faith, a diueliſh faith, an erronious and wicked perſwaſion, and not a true Catholike and Apoſtolike faith.</p>
               <p>Finally, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="42"/> if any man did well vnderſtand the particulars of that Faith, which the Apoſtate ſeeketh to commend to his Countrimen, and which the Church of <hi>England</hi> reiecteth as comming from <hi>Antichrist;</hi> hee might plainely ſee, that the Papiſts are neither Catholikes nor hold the Catholike Faith in any thing, which the Church of <hi>England</hi> diſliketh. Wherefore leaſt any hereafter ſhould boaſt, that his Popiſh religion is Catholike; I will hereafter ſpecifie diuers points thereof which themſelues will be forced to confeſſe to bee vncatholike.</p>
               <div type="appendix">
                  <head>An Appendix vnto the third Chapter, contayning ſome principall points of the vncatholike, moderne <hi>Romiſh</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</head>
                  <p>WHen wee ſpeake againſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and her Doctrine, wee vnderſtand not either the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any Article of her Faith, but the new Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as ſhee is ſubiect to the Pope and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth his new Faith contained in his Decretals, and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the late conuenticle of <hi>Trent,</hi> and is maintained by the Schoole-men and other his factors. And of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine theſe are ſome of the chiefe heads.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> as wee acknowledge <hi>Christ</hi> to be the author and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher of our Faith; ſo Papiſts deriue their Faith from the Pope, as the Author and principall Founder thereof. For whatſoeuer God ſpeaketh to vs in Scriptures, yet they allow nothing, but what the Pope propoundeth.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:238:18"/>
                  <p>We beleeue no head of the Church but <hi>Christ Ieſus,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> who is alſo the Sauiour of his body. They profeſſe the Pope to be the head of the vniuerſall Church.</p>
                  <p>Wee are taught 1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>That Christ Ieſus is the onely foundation of the Church. Stapleton</hi> and his followers beleeue <hi>That the Pope and his determinations are the Churches foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation alſo.</hi> And this is alſo the Doctrine of <hi>Bellarmine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Church being a chaſt virgin admitteth no Spouſe but <hi>Christ Ioſus.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> But the adulterous Sinagogue of <hi>Rome</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the Pope as her Spouſe, as appeareth, <hi>C. Vbi periculum. de elect. in</hi> 6.</p>
                  <p>When any queſtion ariſeth about matters of Faith, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will haue the Pope to be ſupreame Iudge, a matter vnreaſonable, that an Heretike and an enemy ſhould ſit judge in matters of Faith and in his owne cauſe.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Chriſt</hi> aſcended into Heauen, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> they ſay, he left the Pope to be his. Vicar. But of this he ſheweth no commiſſion or proofe.</p>
                  <p>They beleeue alſo, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> that the Pope is S. <hi>Peters</hi> onely Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, and the vniuerſall Biſhop, and chiefe Monarch of the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall Church. But neither doth he teach or loue <hi>Christ.</hi> as did <hi>Peter,</hi> nor doth hee demonſtrate how this vniuerſall Monarchy came vnto him.</p>
                  <p>They ſay he hath power to diſpenſe againſt the Law, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> the Goſpell, and the Apoſtle. And ſo he doth indeed, diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with periured and moſt flagitious men, and neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding Law nor Goſpell, nor what the Apoſtle teacheth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Suarez lib.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 6. <hi>Defenſ. Cath. &amp; Apoſt. fid. c.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. Teacheth that the Pope hath power not onely to depoſe Kings, but to command them to bee killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Christ</hi> fled away when the people ſought to make him King. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> But the Pope challengeth, not onely to be a Biſhop, but a King alſo.</p>
                  <p>The Popes Decretals concerning matters of Faith, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> they ſay are cleare from all errors: ſo doe the <hi>Turkes</hi> alſo thinke of their <hi>Alchoran.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:238:18"/>
                  <p>Of holy Scriptures they ſpeake euill, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> calling them a <hi>dead Letter,</hi> a <hi>dumbe Judge, matter of ſtrife,</hi> a <hi>killing Letter,</hi> a <hi>Noſe of Waxe,</hi> a <hi>Lesbian Rule.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They receiue the vnwritten Traditions of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with equall affection as they receiue holy Scriptures; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> and yet doe they not certainly know them, nor can demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to others what they are.</p>
                  <p>The Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> they ſay, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> is the Rule of Faith: But what Rule then hath this Doctrine? Some ſay, Traditions not written, added to the Scriptures, make vp the entire Rule.</p>
                  <p>They forbid holy Scriptures to be read in vulgar Tongues to the people, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> being afraid belike leaſt the light thereof ſhould diſcouer their falſe errors and foule deeds.</p>
                  <p>Contrarie to the Doctrine of the Fathers, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> they make the Bookes of <hi>Tobia, Iudith, Wiſdome, Eccleſiasticus,</hi> the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees,</hi> and thoſe peeces of Bookes that are in the old vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Latine Tranſlation, and not in the Originals, to be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall Scriptures, equall to the Law and Prophets.</p>
                  <p>The old Latine vulgar Tranſlation they make authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> and neyther the Hebrew nor Greeke Originals of the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
                  <p>They forbid all interpretations of Scriptures, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> contrarie to the ſence of the Pope, and <hi>Roman</hi> Church; and might as well forbid all Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>They teach, that the worſhip of <hi>Dulia</hi> is due to Saints, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> and <hi>Hyperdulia</hi> to the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They worſhip Images of Gold and Siluer, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> and fall downe before the workes of their owne hands.</p>
                  <p>Before a Stock they ſay <hi>Pater noster,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> and before Images of Stone and Mettall, they ſay <hi>Mater nostra;</hi> praying helpe of them, that neyther heare nor ſee, nor walke nor ſpeake.</p>
                  <p>They deſire the Picture of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Face giuen, as is ſaid, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> to <hi>Veromca,</hi> to <hi>blot out their ſinnes,</hi> and to <hi>bring them to the ſocietie of Saints.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:238:19"/>
                  <p>They call vpon Angels and Saints in all places, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> as if they were euery where preſent, and could heare their prayers, and vnderſtand their thoughts, and could helpe.</p>
                  <p>Praying to the Croſſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> they ſay, <hi>Aue ſpes vnica,</hi> and deſire it <hi>to encreaſe inſtice in them,</hi> and <hi>to pardon their ſinnes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They giue diuine honor to the Croſſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> and to the Images of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Trinitie; which is vnexcuſable Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie.</p>
                  <p>Conſecrating a Croſſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> they deſire it may be to them a <hi>Foundation of Faith,</hi> and a <hi>Defence in Aduerſitie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They beleeue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> that the Image of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> can helpe the faithfull, and that the Image of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt <hi>hath power to driue away Diuels;</hi> as appeareth by their prayers in the Pontificall, when they conſecrate them.</p>
                  <p>They pray without vnderſtanding in a ſtrange Tongue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> and call vpon Saints and Angels, that neyther are preſent, nor heare them.</p>
                  <p>They make the Images of the Trinitie; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> and not onely of Angels, but mens ſoules in Heauen.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle ſayth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> there is but one Mediator betwixt God and man; they employ all Angels and Saints, as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators.</p>
                  <p>Yea, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> they call vpon S. <hi>George,</hi> S. <hi>Katherine,</hi> S. <hi>Christo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher,</hi> and XI. M. Virgins, yet are not aſſured, that there are any ſuch Saints in Heauen, or euer were in the World.</p>
                  <p>In the Maſſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> the Prieſt preſumptuouſly taketh vpon him to be a Mediator for <hi>Christ Jeſus,</hi> beſeeching the Father to looke vpon his Sonne with a ſerene countenance, and to ſend Angels to carrie vp his Bodie into Heauen.</p>
                  <p>Maſſe-Prieſts beleeue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/> that they are Prieſts according to the Order of <hi>Melchiſedech;</hi> but the Apoſtle, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7. ſheweth, how that Office belongeth only to <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They beleeue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="34"/> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is by them continually offered to God: but the Apoſtle ſayth he was but once offered, and that by that one Oblation, he perſited all that are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:238:19"/>
                  <p>They offer Maſſes <hi>for the redemption of their Soules,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="35"/> as if men were redeemed by Maſſe-Prieſts, as well as by <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They ſay Maſſes alſo for Hogges, and ſick Horſes: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/> which is an intollerable impietie, preſuming that <hi>Chriſt</hi> dyed for brute Beaſts.</p>
                  <p>They hold the Maſſe to be a Sacrifice propitiatorie; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/> as if ſinnes could be remitted, without bloud: which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle denyeth, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p>S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1. ſayth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/> 
                     <hi>Chriſts bloud doth cleanſe vs from all ſinnes:</hi> quite contrarie to the Doctrine of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts,</hi> holding that ſinnes are cleanſed by Purgatorie fire, and by our owne and the Saints ſufferings.</p>
                  <p>They whip themſelues, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="39"/> thinking by their owne Penance to purge away ſinnes, like <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts; not conſidering, that we are healed by <hi>Chriſts</hi> wounds.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. ſayth, <hi>we are ſaued by grace:</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/> they beleeue, they are ſaued by the merits of their workes.</p>
                  <p>Hee ſayth, <hi>God called vs, not according to our workes,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="41"/> but <hi>according to his purpoſe, and grace:</hi> They hold, that. God doth predeſtinate and call ſuch as by free-will admit that calling, and iuſtifie men that firſt prepare themſelues to iuſtification.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. he ſheweth, <hi>That it is not in him that willeth,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="42"/> 
                     <hi>nor in him that runneth:</hi> They teach, that euery one that will may be ſaued, if he run well.</p>
                  <p>They doe alſo teach, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="43"/> that God giueth ſufficient grace to all to be ſaued: as if euery one were choſen, and called, and had grace giuen him to beleeue.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. ſayth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="44"/> 
                     <hi>We are iuſtified freely by grace, through the redemption that is in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> They beleeue, they are iuſtified by their workes and merits.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> breaking Bread, ſayd, <hi>This is my Body:</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="45"/> Theſe denie that he gaue Bread, or called it his Body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> diſtributed the Cup to all that had receiued the Bread: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="46"/> They ſuffer not any but Prieſts to drinke of the Cup.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:238:20"/>
                  <p>They ſay, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="47"/> 
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> did eate himſelfe and offer himſelfe at his laſt Supper: but for a man to eate himſelfe, it is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd; and for <hi>Chriſt</hi> to offer two Sacrifices, was ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous.</p>
                  <p>In priuate Maſſes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="48"/> the Prieſt doth eate and drinke all alone: but that is contrarie to <hi>Chriſts</hi> Inſtitution.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> bad his Diſciples preach the Goſpel: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="49"/> The Popes Emiſſaries preach Traditions, and Doctrine contrarie to the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>Among Papiſts, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="50"/> Women baptize, and ſometime preach; as <hi>Katherine</hi> of <hi>Siena,</hi> and <hi>Joane</hi> of the Croſſe did.</p>
                  <p>They thinke it is ſufficient to beleeue implicitely. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="51"/> 
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſayd, eternall life conſiſted in knowing <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They beleeue in a God that neyther made Heauen nor Earth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="52"/> and in Chriſt made of Bread, contrarie to the words of the Creed.</p>
                  <p>Prieſts take vpon them to be creators of their Creator; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="53"/> as if they had power ouer God.</p>
                  <p>They beleeue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="54"/> that <hi>Chriſts</hi> Body is in many places at once; as if euery body were not circumſcribed by place, and continued to it ſelfe: now what is this, but to deſtroy <hi>Chriſts</hi> humane Nature?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſts</hi> true Body in the Sacrament, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="55"/> they ſay, neyther ſeeth, nor feeleth, nor moueth. How is that Body then a true humane Body, that hath no ſence nor motion?</p>
                  <p>The Maſſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="56"/> they ſay, is an externall Sacrifice: How then is <hi>Chriſt</hi> offered in the Maſſe, which is not exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſeene?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Capernaites</hi> condemned the reall eating of his fleſh: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="57"/> yet doe Papiſts beleeue, they really eate his fleſh and drinke his bloud with their mouthes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſayth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="58"/> they liue for euer, that eate his fieſh: Yet Papiſts ſay, Reprobates eate his fleſh, which cannot attaine eternall life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="59"/> The Faith of Papiſts being founded on the Pope and his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:238:20"/>Decretals is meerely an humane Faith: and therefore not true Chriſtian Faith.</p>
                  <p>The Cardinals hauing elected a new Pope place him on the Altar, and adore him. Great Princes alſo kiſſe his feet, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="60"/> and common people eſteeme him as a God.</p>
                  <p>They forbid certaine Meates and prohibite their Vota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to Marrie: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="61"/> which the Apoſtle 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. calleth no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then <hi>Doctrines of Diuels.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They teach rebellion againſt Princes excommunicated, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="62"/> contrary to the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. that teacheth Obedience.</p>
                  <p>With their equiuocations and mentall referuations, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="63"/> which they take to bee lawfull, they deceiue not onely pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men, but alſo publike Magiſtrates, affirming, denying, and ſwearing what they liſt without any ſcruple of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; eſpecially, if they take the Iudge to be incompetent, or themſelues not bound to anſwer.</p>
                  <p>Neither doe they thinke it vnlawfull to murther Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate perſons, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="64"/> being moued with zeale toward their mother the Church. <hi>c. Excommunicatorum.</hi> 23. <hi>q.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>The Conuenticle of <hi>Conſtance</hi> giueth them libertie to breake their Oathes made with Heretikes. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="65"/> And the Pope, if any be more ſcrupulous then other, doth eaſily diſpenſe with them in caſes of Periurie.</p>
                  <p>For Hereſie they account it meritorious for Parents to bring word to burne their Children condemned for hereſie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="66"/> and for Children to doe the like to their Parents. They permit for the ſame cauſe Wiues to depart from their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, and husbands from their wiues.</p>
                  <p>Neither doe they make any ſcruple either to defraud their creditors, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="67"/> or to ſpoyle good Chriſtians, if they be cenſured as Heretikes: As <hi>Mariana</hi> and <hi>Philopater</hi> teach.</p>
                  <p>They forbid their Maſſe-Prieſts, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="68"/> Monkes and Friers to marrie: yet cannot they keepe them out of Brodels. Nay, they forbid not publike Stewes, albeit they thinke it a great ſinne for Votaries to marrie.</p>
                  <p>Before Marriage conſummated, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="69"/> they giue permiſſion to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:238:21"/>either of the parties, that are publikely married to betake themſelues to a Monaſticall life.</p>
                  <p>The law of God teacheth Children to honour their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="70"/> But the law of the Popes <hi>Alchoran</hi> permitteth Children either to marrie without their Parents conſent, or to forſake their parents, and to enter into a Monaſtery.</p>
                  <p>For Priſoners to breake priſon, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="71"/> and to breake their word and oath giuen to the Gaoler, they hold to be no ſinne. And this is a common practiſe of Maſſe-Prieſts and their diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They thinke it a ſmall ſinne to ſteale things of ſmall va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="72"/> and to curſe and blaſpheme, if it be done without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditation.</p>
                  <p>They teach, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="73"/> that Penance is not needfull for veniall ſinnes, and that ſuch offences are done away by knocking of the breſt, or by the Biſhops bleſſing, or ſprinkling with Holy water.</p>
                  <p>As if <hi>Christ</hi> had not made ſatisfaction for mens ſinnes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="74"/> they teach, that all muſt ſatisfie for ſinnes committed after Baptiſme, eyther in this life or in Purgatorie.</p>
                  <p>Nay, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="75"/> albeit ſinnes be remitted, yet they hold, that euen iuſt men muſt ſatisfie for the penaltie of ſinne. As if debtors were to pay after the Obligation is taken vp, and they which owe nothing, were to make payment.</p>
                  <p>They teach there are 4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="76"/> 
                     <hi>Stages</hi> or receptacles in Hell, to wit. The 1. of the Damned; the 2. of Purgatorie; the 3. of Children dying before Baptiſme; the 4. for the ſoules of the Patriarkes before <hi>Chriſts</hi> aſcention. But let them beware they make not their Diſciples to doubt of Hell; as their proofes for the other 3. places are weake and doubtfull, and make men deny them.</p>
                  <p>The wiſe-man <hi>Sap.</hi> 3. ſaith, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="77"/> 
                     <hi>The ſoules of the just are in the hands of God, and that no torment toucheth them.</hi> Are they then wiſe, that caſt iuſt men into the fire and torments of Purgatorie.</p>
                  <p>By Maſſes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="78"/> and Indulgences, and Almes, they ſay Soules
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:238:21"/>are drawne out of Purgatorie: as if S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and ancient Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> had ſung Maſſes and granted Indulgences to Soules in Purgatorie, or Soules might be freed out of Hell, which comprehendeth Purgatorie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſay they, inſtituted Indulgences, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="79"/> but they know not where. The Conuenticle of <hi>Trent</hi> ſayth alſo, <hi>they are wholeſome and profitable;</hi> but the <hi>Germans</hi> in <hi>Grauam.</hi> 3. denie it.</p>
                  <p>In the Taxe of the Popes Chamber there is a Rate ſet downe, what is to be payd for Inceſt, Periurie, Parricides, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="80"/> and all ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>From the <hi>Iewes,</hi> they borrow Altars, Prieſtly Orders, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="81"/> and Apparrell, burning of Incenſe, offering of Paſchall Lambes, and ſuch like Traditions.</p>
                  <p>Sacrifices for the Dead, Purgatorie, conſecrated Water, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="82"/> and ſuch like, ſeeme to proceed from the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> rather then from the later <hi>Iewes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> had the Keyes of the Church committed vnto him, the Pope inferreth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="83"/> that he hath power to make Lawes to diſpenſe againſt Law, to diſpenſe with perſons periured, to diſſolue Matrimonie, and to depriue Princes of their Crownes.</p>
                  <p>Monkes and Fryars, albeit they liue wickedly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="84"/> yet boaſt of their workes of ſupererogation, and hold their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be a ſtate of perfection.</p>
                  <p>Generally they eſtabliſh their iuſtice of Workes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent Charitie: the iuſtice of God, in remitting ſinnes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="85"/> and imputing vnto vs <hi>Chriſts</hi> iuſtice, they regard not.</p>
                  <p>And leaſt any man ſhould except againſt them for this wicked Doctrine, they giue out, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="86"/> that the Pope defining <hi>ex Cathedra,</hi> cannot erre, and that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the ground and pillar of Truth: matters moſt abſurd and falſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Finally, vnleſſe the Apostate can proue, that theſe Doctrines which are aboue ſpecified, are Catholike, himſelfe must needes confeſſe, that neither the Papiſts are Catholikes, nor their Faith Catholike, or true.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:238:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> The Examination of the Apostates Title page and his Epistle dedicatorie.</head>
               <p>THus hauing declared that S. <hi>Austine</hi> either knew not the Apoſtates <hi>Popiſh</hi> religion, or elſe oppugned it, and that Papiſts cannot by any meanes be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Catholikes, beleeuing and teaching as they doe, it followeth now that we enter into the liſtes with this Confeſſioniſt, and examine his whole proceedings.</p>
               <p>In the fore-front and title Page of his booke he promiſeth a <hi>Tranſlation of S.</hi> Auguſtines <hi>Confeſſions.</hi> But how fooliſh he was and euill aduiſed to vndertake this worke, both that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father himſelfe, and this Diſcourſe enſuing will declare. I haue alſo partly touched this point heretofore. Here it will be ſufficient to remember, that hee maketh his Confeſſions to God onely, and not to Angels or Saints, or to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> as this idle fellow and his mates vſe to doe. He ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his ſinnes knowne to God: theſe fellowes thinke they are bound to confeſſe all their ſinnes in the Prieſts eares. All his deuotion was to God, who could forgiue ſinnes: this Apoſtates deuotion is toward the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and to Saints, to whom, if hee be in his right wits, he will not giue power to abſolue him from his ſinnes. Hee conſecrated his confeſſions to God: this Apoſtate doth conſecrate himſelfe and his tranſlation to the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A tranſlation I ſay, ſo idle, falſe, malicious and full of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, that he durſt not ſet his name vnto it. Which I take to be done with ſome cunning, the man (percaſe) meaning to deny it.</p>
               <p>Hee vaunteth that <hi>his large Preface will make the Booke more profitable and pleaſant.</hi> But it had beene farre better, if it had beene ſhorter; for of harſh and foppiſh Prefaces the ſhorteſt are beſt. His Diſcourſe is full of obſeruations falſe, vnpleaſant, full of poyſon and hurtfull, if any of his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:238:22"/>readers bee ſo fooliſh as to giue eare and credit vnto them.</p>
               <p>For his Motto or word, hee ſetteth downe this ſentence; <hi>Cibus ſum grandium, I am meat for the ſtrong, grow and thou ſhalt eate mee.</hi> As if his tranſlation and notes were meat for great men, and ſit to bee deuoured of them: which are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but huskes for ſwine and hoggiſh and ignorant Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts. S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> applyeth theſe words to God, this Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate applyeth them to himſelfe and his idle fantaſies.</p>
               <p>Intimating that his Booke was printed <hi>Permiſſu ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> by <hi>the permiſſion of his Superiours,</hi> hee maketh a plaine declaration, that like a falſe-hearted fellow hee renounceth his allegiance to his Prince, and ſubmitteth himſelfe to trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Maſſe-Prieſts and Ieſuites, and other the Popes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine factors, enemies to the Prince and State.</p>
               <p>Now come we to the Epiſtle dedicatory directed to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> a worke full of preſumption and vanity. For how could ſo holy a Virgin accept of ſuch an impure companion; or ſo faithfull a Chriſtian, allow of this diſciple of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> endeuouring to draw Chriſtians from <hi>Christ</hi> to ſerue <hi>Belial?</hi> Further how can ſo ſpotleſſe a Virgin ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue ſo corrupt a Tranſlation, and ſo wicked a Preface, and notes ſauouring of nothing, but the ſpirit of Sathan, ſeeking by lyes and impoſtures to abuſe the ſimple.</p>
               <p>This bleſſed Virgin hee ſlileth the <hi>moſt glorious Queene of Heauen.</hi> A ſtile neyther giuen to her by the Apoſtles, nor allowed by any Catholike; further, it is a vaine imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to turne the Kingdome of Heauen into an earthly Princes Court, and to ſuppoſe that God is married to a woman.</p>
               <p>He addeth, that <hi>ſhee is the joy of coeleſtiall Spirits,</hi> and <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſt the higheſt hope of humane creatures.</hi> As if Angels turned themſelues from God, to ioy in the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or men were chiefly to hope in her. Where did this man learne this tradition, and how doth hee proue, that Angels and men are to ioy in a Creature, and to truſt in her, and not to place their glory and hope in God onely. Is this a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:238:23"/>point of Doctrine? and will his holy Father define it to bee true?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behold,</hi> ſayth hee, <hi>a prodigall Child of thine.</hi> As if ſuch a wanton young-man, that hath ſo often runne from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, were the Sonne of a Virgin, and <hi>a glorious Queene,</hi> as he calleth her, who neuer had any ſonne but him, that was alſo the Sonne of God. A <hi>prodigall Child,</hi> hee may well call himſelfe, as one that hath <hi>diſſipated his ſubſtance, viuendo luxurioſe,</hi> and which hath <hi>deuoured his ſubſtance, cum mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricibus,</hi> as did the Prodigall mentioned <hi>Luk.</hi> 15. But let him forbeare to call himſelfe (a man ſo debauched) the holy Virgins ſonne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In ſtead of a glaſſe of Flowers,</hi> as he ſayth, hee <hi>layeth vpon the altar of the Virgins goodneſſe a booke of Pictures, which haue the fame to bee well limned.</hi> But firſt, it is boyes play, to make ſport with Glaſſes, Flowers and Puppets. Next, in earneſt he declareth himſelfe to bee an Idolater, that ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth an Altar to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and offereth ſacrifice vpon it. Thirdly, were he not an Ideote, hee would not make S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> a limner; and if he were not vayne-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, he would not ſuppoſe, that this vayne Tranſlation were a picture well limned, or compare ſuch brutiſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits to Flowers odoriferous, and Pictures beautifull and glorious.</p>
               <p>Going on in his abſurd allegoriſing vayne, hee telleth vs, <hi>That the colours of the Pictures were mingled by no worſe hand then of the holy Ghost, and layd by one of his fore-fingers.</hi> As if this abſurd and miſhapen tranſlation were painted out with freſh colours, or ſuch a diſcolute and diſcompoſed Painter were a fore-finger of the Holy Ghoſt, or the Holy Ghoſt had hands and fore-fingers to paint withall. Further, to ſpeake of S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> himſelfe, he was not ſo bold as to ſay, his <hi>Confeſſions</hi> were indited by the Holy Ghoſt, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth onely to the ſublime authority of holy canonicall Scriptures. Neyther was he ſo groſſe conceited, as to make the Holy Ghoſt in the forme of a man, or to attribute to him
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:238:23"/>the Art of Limning. This is the worke of this painting Apoſtate, who hauing rinegued Chriſ, maketh no ſcruple to blaſpheme the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>Further, hee ſayth, <hi>his wandering youth in faith and life, doth not diſcourage him from venturing his tranſlation before the-Virgins eyes.</hi> He would haue ſayd venting, if he could haue hit vpon the word, for Marchant venturer he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: neyther had he reaſon to venture the ſight of ſo baudie a Worke, before ſuch a <hi>Queene</hi> as he imagineth her to be; and ſo contemptible a tranſlation, before her curious iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Further, how doth he proue, that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> would or could reade his Booke below, ſhee reigning in Heauen aboue? And what teſtimonie can he produce, that he doth not now more wander and goe aſtray both in faith and life, then he did in his moſt youthfull time? <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> certes are no places to teach reformation, eyther in Doctrine or manners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou flowest from that Sea of Mercie,</hi> ſayth he, ſpeaking of the Virgin <hi>Mary, as a most noble and nauigable Riuer, bearing Bottomes of all Burthens:</hi> So he blaſphemeth that holy Virgin, ſuppoſing her to be a nauigable Riuer, bearing Popiſh, Turkiſh, and Pagan Bottomes, and diſhonouring her Virginitie, whom he would ſeeme to magnifie. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, like a ridiculous Sot, he maketh nauigable Riuers to flow out of the Sea; which his ſences, if hee haue any, might haue ſhewed him to flow into the Sea, He doth alſo make the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> to flow from the Diuinitie, as if ſhe were a fourth Perſon in the Trinitie, or as if ſhe were her Sonnes Image.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Christ,</hi> ſayth hee, <hi>payd the price of our redemption out of the ſtocke of his fleſh and bloud which he tooke from his Mother:</hi> As if our Sauiour acted nothing with his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, and holy Soule, in the Act of our Redemption, and all his ſtocke had come from her, and ſhee, and not <hi>Christ, had broken the Serpents head.</hi> Theſe are not Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies, but Blaſphemies, of which he hath no ſmall ſtocke,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:238:24"/>the ſtocke of his ſubſtance being formerly ſpent in foraine Countries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His mercie,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>ſo lookes, as if his iustice did receiue thereby ſome wrong:</hi> as if <hi>Chriſts</hi> iuſtice could not ſtand with his mercie. Further, he diminiſheth much of <hi>Chriſts</hi> mercie, making not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but the Virgin <hi>Mary, a naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable Riuer of Mercie, capable of all Bottomes.</hi> It may be he thinketh, that as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaued all Chriſtians, ſo the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> ſaued Turkes, Infidels, and Apoſtates.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Saint repayred the ruines of his former life, and as a broken Bough being bound about, exceeded in ſtrength,</hi> as hee telfeth the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> But S. <hi>Austine</hi> neuer told the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> ſo much, nor did he confeſſe to her, as this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate doth confeſſe for him, but without commiſſion. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it was not in S. <hi>Austines</hi> power to repayre himſelfe; nor are broken Boughes, being ingrafted, ſtronger then they were before: were he and his companions ingrafted in <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne</hi> Stocks, they would neyther grow ſtrong nor long.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S.</hi> Auguſtine <hi>retracted ſome of his words:</hi> But what hath the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> to doe with his retractations? this ſhould rather be an example for the Tranſlator to retract his Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and repent himſelfe of his Apoſtacie. He addeth, <hi>that he reuerſed all the impure workes of his heart:</hi> as if it lay in man, to make his heart cleane, and to repent. This is impure <hi>Pelagianiſme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He addeth, <hi>that S.</hi> Auſtine <hi>gaue himſelfe, as it were, into the hands of the foure Winds, to ſpread him abroad as a moſt wicked peece of fleſh.</hi> As if no Winds did blow but foure, and theſe Winds had Hands, and S. <hi>Austine</hi> had more wicked fleſh then the Tranſlator and his Conſorts. He may therefore thinke himſelfe happie, that the bleſſed Virgin ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no note of his words: for if ſhe ſhould reward him according to his deeds, ſhe ſhould for his madneſſe commit him to <hi>Bedlem,</hi> there to be whipped by foure Beadles, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till his wicked and luxurious fleſh were well chaſtiſed for his windie conceits.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:238:24"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Such humilitie (as thou, O ſacred Virgin, doeſt beſt know) cannot chuſe but now be anſwered with a ſtrange meaſure of glorie.</hi> But firſt, how doth the Tranſlator know, that the bleſſed Virgin was beſt acquainted with S. <hi>Austines</hi> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie and his thoughts? Did ſhee better know it, then God Almightie, the ſearcher of mens hearts? Further, who can ſay, that by his humilitie he can deſerue a <hi>ſtrange mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of glorie?</hi> S. <hi>Austine</hi> certes was neuer of this mans humor, who truſted rather to Gods mercy, then to his owne merites.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He did penetrate the conſideration of thy matchleſſe puritie with a most perfect eye, which in dignitie is next to God,</hi> ſayth he, ſpeaking to the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> As if this blind Buzzard, which hath neyther perfect eye, nor other good ſence, could penetrate S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> conceit concerning the Virgins puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or diſcerne who is next to God in dignitie. That the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was conceiued without ſinne, S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> neuer ſayd; nor doth he preferre her in dignitie, before Angels. Nay, that exception which is now found put into his 36. <hi>Chapt. de Natura &amp; Gratia,</hi> ſeemeth to be foyſted in by ſome Fryar.-Further, S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> doth neyther accuſe her, nor excuſe her. Nay, <hi>c.</hi> 41. out of <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. he proueth, <hi>that ſinne by one man paſſed ouer all.</hi> No where was he ſo ſimple, as to talke of <hi>the perfect eye of the Virgins Soule;</hi> of which the Apoſtate, whoſe Soule is dyed in villanie, ſpeaketh: nor doth hee ſay, that her Soule <hi>was wholly free from the least ſhadow of ſpot:</hi> or, that hee that ſhould charge the bleſſed Virgin <hi>with any ſinne, ſhould ſtrip our Sauiour of his honour;</hi> as this ſhameleſſe companion, ſtripping all ſhame from his face, moſt falſely affirmeth: for hee hath nothing of the <hi>ſhadowes of ſpots.</hi> Nor was it any diſhonour for <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be borne of a ſinfull Woman, ſhe being ouer ſhadowed by the holy Ghoſt, when ſhe conceiued <hi>Chriſt:</hi> but that her Mother was ouer-ſhadowed by the holy Ghoſt, when ſhe conceiued her, we reade not, nor can it be proued.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He beleeueth,</hi> as he ſayth, <hi>that the holy Virgin was as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:238:25"/>immaculate in the first instant of her Conception, as ſhe is truly glorious by her Aſſumption.</hi> Which argueth, that he is a poore Infidell, hauing no Faith, but that which is built vpon the Dreames of Fryars, and Fables, concerning her Aſſumption. Dreames, I ſay, and Fables, contradicted by many of the moſt learned of his owne ſide, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by any true Chriſtians, that build their Faith vpon the Word of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The times wherein we liue,</hi> he ſayth, <hi>are deadly ſicke of two Infirmities.</hi> Which wee confeſſe to be true, in himſelfe and his Conſorts: who offend ſo outragiouſly in Luxurie and Hereſie, that ſcarce Pagans come neere them in the firſt, or the ancient Heretikes in the ſecond; maintaining publike Brothels, and giuing themſelues ouer to all vncleanneſſe. They doe alſo oppugne the true Faith, and vphold moſt damnable Hereſies. And this is not onely found true by experience, but alſo teſtified by <hi>Petrarch, Boccace, Platina,</hi> and their owne Writers, and that in Popes, Cardinals, Maſſe-Prieſts, and the moſt eminent men of that ſide. Let S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> reade what <hi>Lecture</hi> he will vpon <hi>the Anatomie of the Soule,</hi> yet if his Soule and Bodie were anatomized, there would be nothing found therein, but Botches, Vlcers, Scabs, and a whole maſſe of filthineſſe and villanie. If then he had any drops of bloud left vncorrupted he would bluſh and be aſhamed to talke of anatomizing Soules, and of deadly ſickneſſes, himſelfe and his Mates being moſt of all therewith infected, and ruined. But were he neuer ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſed, and needed he neuer ſo much to be carryed to the Hoſpitall, yet hath he no reaſon, as he doth, to call her <hi>an Hoſpitall,</hi> which commonly is a Receptacle of ſicke, ſcabbed, and vlcered companions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There was neuer,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>within the Line and Latitude of meere Creatures, ſo bright a Beame of Truth ſhot out from the Spheare of immortall Light, nor ſo cleare a Streame of Puritie from theeuerlasting Spring of Paradiſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as that which did ſill and euerflow thy most holy Soule; the high
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:238:25"/>example and ſweet influxe whereof, doth ſo helpe to reforme and rectifie the darke and diſſolute heart of man.</hi> And I, to requite his fluxe of vanitie in part, ſay, you ſhall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finde ſuch a peece of bombaſted Barbariſme, ſuch a Line of doltiſh Dizardrie, and ſuch a frame of allegorizing Pedantrie, as this extrauagant Tranſlator hath here affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs: Draw out your Lines, and vſe your vttermoſt Art, yet ſhall you not frame a Modell of a Dizard com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to him. Who euer could ſhoot out ſuch Bolts of Foolerie, and flow with ſuch exceſſe of Inke-pot phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but hee, that is ſteeped in the Popes Cloſe-Stoole, and ſhaped by the Rules of irregular <hi>Ignatians?</hi> The bleſſed Virgin hee diſgraceth with his exorbitant phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and maketh an Idoll of her whom he deſireth to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie; ſignifying, that Grace did flowe from her, as a Goddeſſe.</p>
               <p>Hee prayeth to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> that <hi>neyther the Mist or Fogge of Senſualitie may detaine him, nor the ſide Wind of Vanitie diuert him, nor the contrarie Wind of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience toſſe him: as for the Pyrate of Hereſie, he preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth he needeth no more to feare, least he be drowned by him.</hi> But had wee no other argument to diſproue the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> this one were ſufficient to ouerthrow it: for notwithſtanding all his importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, wee ſee hee is ouerwhelmed with Miſts and Fogges of Luſt and Concupiſcence; his Vanitie and Pride hath diuerted him from all Goodneſſe, contrarie Windes and Diſcontent hath bereaued him of his Sences, and neuer was any of his Conſorts more deepely plunged into Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. But ſo it fareth with thoſe, which leauing <hi>Christ Jeſus,</hi> the Fountaine of liuing Water, digge to themſelues Ceſtern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s that hold no Water, and flye to the interceſſion of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> of Angels and Saints.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:238:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Herein the Apoſtates abſurd tedious and malicious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face is ſcanned and refuted.</head>
               <p>THE principall marke vnto which the Prefator and Tranſlator directeth all his bolts; is firſt, to proue himſelfe and his Popiſh conſorts to bee <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes,</hi> and next to conuince his Parents, good friends and Countrimen to be misbeleeuers and Heretikes.</p>
               <p>But how farre wide he ſhooteth in the firſt, I haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by ſound arguments declared. The ſame will alſo more euidently appeare by the anſwer made to his Obiections, and by the whole Diſcourſe enſuing. The ſecond ſhall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly bee demonſtrated as well by our publike Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which containe nothing but ſound <hi>Catholike</hi> doctrine, as by his vayne friuolous and calumnious oppoſition in his Preface and idle Annotations. See then I pray you the pride and preſumption of this rinegate, who at his firſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth, taketh that as granted, which in all his tedious Diſcourſe he ſhall neuer be able to proue. For how can hee call himſelfe and his fellowes Catholikes, whoſe Doctrines reiected by vs are a compoſition of old and new Hereſies? And how can hee deny vs that title, whoſe Faith is wholly Catholike and Apoſtolike?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hee preſenteth vs,</hi> as hee profeſſeth, <hi>with a tranſlation of S.</hi> AVSTINES <hi>Confeſſions.</hi> A poore preſent, God wot, and nothing worth our acceptance, being firſt as it ſeemeth rather turned out of <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> then <hi>Latine,</hi> and next diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from the Originall in diuers places; and thirdly, being corrupted with falſe Notes and gloſſes. Hee preſumeth it will be profitable and not vnpleaſing; ſo Geefe beleeue their owne Goſlings to be goodly birds. He addeth, that <hi>the ſubject will bee now and then hard.</hi> As if euery Schoole-boy could not tranſlate S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Confeſſions, as well as hee, or any Diſcourſe could be more eaſie.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:238:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>As the beauty of a perſon,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>conſiſteth in Complexion, proportion, and motion.</hi> So he would proue S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> to bee excellent in the <hi>complexion of his Soule, the proportion of the parts of his Booke,</hi> and <hi>the actions of his Life.</hi> A ſimilitude borrowed from his skill in diſcerning the beautie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion of his out-landiſh Miſtreſſes, but euill befitting this Subiect. For firſt, what likeneſſe is there betweene Men and Bookes? Secondly, when did he euer ſee the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion of S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Soule? Thirdly, what beauty is there in the diſtinction of the Chapters made by ſome ignorant tranſcriber of S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Confeſſions? Laſtly, what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this tale of <hi>faire Complexion, decent proportion and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to his euill fauoured tranſlation, and jeiune Preface and Notes?</p>
               <p>He <hi>pitieth ſome Critickes offended,</hi> as hee ſaith, <hi>with ſome tautologies of this Booke;</hi> But ſuch Critickes pitie rather the tranſlators Morologies and Pſeudologies, handling an argument vnfit for ſuch a perſon, and with diuers lies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending his owne friends, and taxing his aduerſaries.</p>
               <p>Vanting of his labours he ſaith, <hi>It was not in his will to commit the leaſt fault:</hi> but what if ignorance and partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie haue caried him into faults and errours: ſhall wee accept his will for excuſe? In the Preface and Tranſlation you ſhall find faults, lyes, and corruptions, ſuch as will eaſily conuince this vayne brag.</p>
               <p>Hee taxeth ſome <hi>for falſifying and corrupting S.</hi> Auſtines <hi>bookes, De ciuit. Dei, and his Meditations.</hi> But his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe is eaſily anſwered. For firſt, he doth not, nor cannot ſhew any proofe of the corruption of S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> bookes, <hi>de ciuit. Dei.</hi> Secondly, the booke of <hi>Meditations</hi> attributed to him, is not his. I haue ſeene it vnder the name of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelme.</hi> Others attribute it to ſome later Schoole-man; and Maſter <hi>Rogers</hi> doth not ſo much tranſlate the booke of <hi>Meditations,</hi> as frame a new Diſcourſe vpon that ground.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>that the beleefe and practiſe of S.</hi> AVGVSTINE, <hi>and the Church of his time, is fully agreeable to the</hi> Roman
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:238:27"/>
                  <hi>Church at this day, and different from the Church of</hi> England, as he affirmeth, cannot bee proued out of any of S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> workes. This I haue cleerely demonſtrated before. Now I ſay onely hee cannot proue, eyther the myſteries of the Maſſe, or the Popes vniuerſall Monarchy, or the 7. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and Indulgences, or the Decrees of <hi>Trent</hi> which wee refuſe. Onely it is eaſily proued, that hee is an aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary of this Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſo hee profeſſeth himſelfe to bee. He is alſo an enemy of his Countrey and the State, and a ſlaue of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> albeit hee doth not profeſſe it.</p>
               <p>Hee complaineth of <hi>the great difficulty of Tranſlating this Booke;</hi> and yet a Child of 15. yeares old might well haue tranſlated a harder Booke then this. And if his betters thought ſo, as well as himſelfe, both hee and his betters were poore, weake and ignorant Tranſlators.</p>
               <p>The ſentences of S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Confeſſions are no ſuch deepe matters, but they may eaſily be vnderſtood. But to find <hi>Sentences, that grew on the tree of S.</hi> AVSTINES <hi>ſoule,</hi> and <hi>to gather them with Flewers</hi> and <hi>dowe vpon them,</hi> is an abſurd conceit, and altogether impoſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le. Neuer were any ſuch Trees, Flower, or Dew heard of, but in the Apoſtates harſh ſtile. Let him rather beware of ſentences growing out of <hi>Tiburne</hi> tree, and of treacherous Doctrines taught him by Maſſe-Prieſts, Monkes and Ignatians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hauing finiſhed the Tranſlation, he found,</hi> as he confeſſeth, <hi>That hee had much miſtaken the ſence of diuers places.</hi> And euery man that is not obdurat, will yeeld, that hee ſayth it truely. But that he reformed his miſtakings, it apeareth not. Nay, we iuſtly doubt he made the matter worſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By his moſt ſignificant and ſententious ſoule,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>his penne is thrust into ſo little roome.</hi> A ſtrange and monſtrous kind of guibriſh, for who euer heard before of a <hi>ſignificant and ſententious ſoule,</hi> and <hi>a penne thrust into a little roome?</hi> but if S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſpoke ſignificantly, how could hee ſpeake ſo obſcurely, as is pretended? If the Apoſtates tongue were
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:238:27"/>wedged in a wimble hole, would he ſpeake darke ſentences thinke you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Hereſie of the</hi> Manichees, ſaith he, <hi>is layd vnder the aſhes of obliuion.</hi> And yet in his Popiſh doctrine concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning prohibition of Mariage to elected Prieſts, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending of <hi>Chriſts</hi> body into diuers places, in the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Chriſts</hi> humane nature, and the Communion vnder one kind, it is againe reuiued.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The arguments of the Chapters,</hi> hee ſaith, <hi>are not S.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtines. A very profound Speculation. He might alſo haue added, that the meaning expreſſed in his Tranſlation is not S. <hi>Auguſtines,</hi> but that ſhall appeare hereafter.</p>
               <p>Going about to commend his Booke of Confeſſions, hee ſaith, <hi>He will borrow the wordes of</hi> Ribadineira. And I doubt hee borrowed ſome light from his <hi>Spaniſh</hi> tranſlation. But if he had choſen out a hundred, hee could not haue encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred a more wicked enemy of Religion and the State, nor a more falſe and treacherous companion then that <hi>Jeſuwide,</hi> who tranſlated and amplified that ſcandalous Libell of <hi>Sanders, De ſchiſmate,</hi> deuiſed of purpoſe to the diſgrace of the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and this State.</p>
               <p>The Ieſuite compareth <hi>his Learning to a Spring, that riſeth and runneth perpetually.</hi> And yet Maſſe-Prieſts and Fryars drinke rather of the puddle Decretals of the Pope, then of S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> cleare Spring.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hauing vowed Chaſtitie to God,</hi> ſayth the Tranſlator, <hi>he retyred, in the companie of two friends, into a ſolitarie houſe, where he ſpent three yeeres in meditation of Scripture, Prayer, Faſting, and other Penance.</hi> But firſt, it is moſt vntrue, that he vowed Chaſtitie, or other Monkiſh Vowes: ſecondly, he was no longer there, then he pleaſed himſelfe: thirdly, he read Scriptures, which Monkes vſe not much to doe now: fourthly, he was not ſubiect to the Pope, nor liued vnder any certaine Rule: fiftly, he whipped not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as the Fryars now doe: ſixtly, he retyred not into a ſolitarie houſe, but into his owne houſe, as <hi>Poſſidonius</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:238:28"/>Was hee not then aſhamed to tell ſo many vntruths with one breath?</p>
               <p>He addeth, <hi>that a principall Caualier offered to depend on his aduice, in the way of ſpirit; and that there were many Monasteries alreadie erected in S.</hi> Auſtines <hi>time.</hi> A groſſe Leaſing, deuiſed not without the inſtigation of ſome wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Spirit. For firſt, the Monaſteries of <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Syria</hi> were of another faſhion: ſecondly, <hi>Benct</hi> brought the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Monkes firſt into <hi>Italie:</hi> thirdly, <hi>Poſſidonius</hi> calleth the man, <hi>Agentem in Rebus, A Factor for the Emperour:</hi> fourthly, of the dependance vpon S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> by way of ſpirit, there is no mention in <hi>Poſſidonius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another groſſe Leaſing, related by the Tranſlator, is that which is related concerning <hi>a Monaſterie built by S.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine <hi>in a Garden; Poſſidonius</hi> ſayth, it was in the Church: and there liued not Canons regular, as this irregular and prodigall fellow reporteth, but ſome ſeruants of God, that followed the Apoſtles rule, and not the faſhions of Monkes, or the Decrees of Popes.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Order of Priesthood</hi> he tooke, but not the Orders of Maſſe-Prieſts, <hi>ſacrificing for quicke and dead:</hi> Nay, he preached the Goſpel, which Maſſe-Prieſts doe not; and was made Biſhop without any Bulls of the Pope, being choſen by the Clergie and People. That <hi>Euangelicall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> conſiſteth in Monaſticall Obedience, hee neuer thought: nor did hee found <hi>a Monasterie, for Canons Regular.</hi> Theſe be Fictions, and Lyes, deuiſed by the Apoſtate for the maintenance of his Popiſh Religion; the <hi>North-ſtarre</hi> of his Diſcourſe, by which hee directeth his broken Barke.</p>
               <p>He confeſſeth, <hi>that hee was frequent in Preaching, Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing and teaching of youth.</hi> A plaine conuiction of the ſloath and negligence of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> woluiſh Prelates, which neither Preach nor Teach, nor Catechiſe. He addeth, <hi>that hee compounded Differences, and exerciſed himſelfe in workes of Charity.</hi> But <hi>Popiſh</hi> Prelats enflame Warres, vexe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:238:28"/>poore Chriſtians, Murther Innocents and are voyd of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and full of vices and villany. That <hi>his Biſhoppricke</hi> ſhould be worth 40. M. <hi>Crownes</hi> by the yeare, is a pleaſant conceit of a fooliſh Factor of the Pope, meaſuring times paſt, wherein the Church was poore and needy, with the time preſent, wherein <hi>Popiſh</hi> Prelates exceed in Luxurie and Pride.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To error in beleefe and ſenſuality of Life,</hi> he confeſſeth, <hi>hee was admirably oppoſite.</hi> To which the Apoſtate and his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts are admirably addicted, being Heretikes by profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſenſuall Epicures in life and conuerſation. Yet did S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> neuer vant of <hi>his noble Cooperation</hi> with Gods grace, or ſay he made <hi>a ſuperabundant ſatisfaction for his former offences.</hi> Theſe bee glorious vaunts of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Heretikes, which take to themſelues power of ſatisfactions and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites due to <hi>Christ.</hi> Hee maketh S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> alſo <hi>vnſpeakably pure,</hi> from a <hi>Papiſt</hi> turning to be a <hi>Puritane,</hi> and giueth that to S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that he neuer tooke to himſelfe. He addeth, that S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> did <hi>expiate</hi> 16. <hi>yeares of his Youth vncleanly ſpent.</hi> As if a man were able to purge his ſinnes, and to make an attonement for them. Making S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and a teacher of perfect Iuſtice; the firſt being Blaſphemy, and the ſecond <hi>Pelagian</hi> Hereſie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the tenderneſſe of S.</hi> Auſtines <hi>Conſcience, and the rigour vſed by him in examination of his ſmall imperfections,</hi> hee talketh idly; himſelfe and his Conſorts hauing Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſeared with hot yrons, and not examining their moſt flagitious Offences, following ſenſuall Luſts, falſifying their Words and Oathes, murthering Gods Saints, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Stewes, teaching Rebellion and open wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He accumulated,</hi> ſayth the Apoſtate, <hi>a huge ſtocke of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites.</hi> But S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> alwayes diſauowed his owne Merites and fled to Gods mercy. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 36. hee ſaith, <hi>All thinges are to bee eſteemed vile to vs, when wee conſider what we are to receiue. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t juſti ficrent merita non fuerunt,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 150. And in his Preface in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31. <hi>Nihil boni
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:238:29"/>feciſti &amp; datur tibi remiſſio peccatorum.</hi> And <hi>de Verb. Apoſt. Serm.</hi> 2. hee ſayth, <hi>God doth crowne vs in pitie and mercie:</hi> of a ſtocke of Merites, he neuer ſpoke one word. Nay, ſo abſurd is the Doctrine of Merites of condignitie, that the ſounder Schoole-men doe diſauow it.</p>
               <p>Hee addeth, <hi>That he came not ſhort in paying his Debts contracted with God and his Church, by reaſon of his erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Beleefe.</hi> But if he came not ſhort of payment, what needed he to begge forgiueneſſe of Debts? If he confuted <hi>Pelagius,</hi> and other Heretikes, then he was no great friend of Papiſts, that teaching puritie of Life, and perfection of Iuſtice, and the power of Free-will in our Regeneration, and doing good Workes, ioyne with <hi>Pelagius,</hi> and other Heretikes, condemned by S. <hi>Auſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> as he ſayth, pretended, <hi>that the vniuerſall Church hath erred, and was periſhed:</hi> But he lyeth groſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for they onely ſayd, that it erred, and periſhed in all places ſaue in <hi>Afrike:</hi> not as Papiſts ſay, that it is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, and erreth in all places, ſaue in the Popes Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hee eſtabliſheth,</hi> ſayth hee, <hi>the ſupreme Authoritie vnder God, of the true, viſible, and vniuerſall Church of Chriſt, in matters of Faith.</hi> But if the true Church were viſible in S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> time, then is not the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of Popes, Cardinals, Inquiſitors, dumbe Prelates, ſacrificing Maſſe-Prieſts, Monkes, Fryars, Nunnes, fierie <hi>Ignatians,</hi> and ſuch Vermine, the true Church; for ſuch a Church was not viſible in S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> time, nor long after. If the Churches Authoritie be Supreme, then is not the Pope Supreme; nay, God ſpeaking in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, is not Supreme. Finally, if the Church be Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall, then is it not confined within the Limits of the Popes Authoritie. Saint <hi>Austine</hi> certes neuer belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Popes ſupreme Iudgement, nor thought the Church of <hi>Afrike</hi> to be of leſſe Authoritie then that of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:238:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Concerning the Canon of Scripture it ſelfe, or the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation or interpretation thereof, or the tryall of Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Tradition, or whatſoeuer other Point in difference; by the iudgement of great Saint</hi> Auguſtine, <hi>the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like viſible Church is that which must be reſorted vnto, as the Supreme and finall Judge on Earth,</hi> as hee ſayth. Hee telleth vs alſo, <hi>That hee gaue certaine generall Rules, whereby all Controuerſies of Faith may bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</hi> But firſt, the Pope doth much ſcorne to follow Saint <hi>Auſtines</hi> Rules, or Iudgement. Secondly, Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> neuer knew any Rule of Controuerſies, but holy Scriptures: <hi>The Rule of Faith,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de Ciuit. Dei, c.</hi> 33. <hi>is ſufficiently knowne to the Faithfull, by the Bookes of Canonicall Scriptures; A Regula Fidei, quae per alias eiuſdem Authoritatis Sacras Literas, ſatis fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nota est non vberrauimus.</hi> Thirdly, Saint <hi>Austine, Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Doctr. Christ. c.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15. and <hi>Lib.</hi> 15. <hi>de Ciuit. c.</hi> 13. will haue Tranſlations examined by the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginals, and inferiour to them. Fourthly, the blinde Papiſts doe not follow the Iudgement of the Catholike viſible Church, but of one blinde Pope, that is the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie of the Church. Fiftly, how can the Vniuerſall Church conuene, to iudge all Controuerſies? And what reaſon hath any to follow the Church before Chriſt; or to heare the Church, iudging in her owne Cauſe? Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Traditions of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, concerning the Popes power, the Maſſe, and ſiue new Sacraments, and their formes and matter, were neuer knowne, eyther to the ancient Church, or to Saint <hi>Auſtine.</hi> Seuenthly, hee neuer knew the Moderne Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or beleeued, that the Catholike Church was viſible, or ſupreme and finall Iudge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hee declareth, what a pestilent thing Hereſie and Schiſme is,</hi> as the Apoſtate confeſſeth. But what is that to vs, that are true Catholikes, and maintaine the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Apoſtolike Church? It toucheth rather the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:238:30"/>peſtilencie of this Apoſtate and his Companions, who hauing abandoned <hi>Chriſt,</hi> adhere to <hi>Antichrist.</hi> and beeing diuided from the Apoſtolike Church, embrace the Hereſies of <hi>Trent,</hi> and Schooles in part condemned, or elſe not knowne to the ancient Catholike Church, or to S. <hi>Auſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> held that which in his time was taught by the Fathers, and was beleeued by the vniuerſall Church. But this Rinegate and his adherents embrace the nouelties of Schooles, and errors of the Pope, and the Conuenticle of <hi>Trent,</hi> albeit they were neuer beleeued by the Church, nor taught by the Fathers. And of theſe erroneous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines I haue touched many particulars heretofore.</p>
               <p>That holy Father, <hi>Lib. de vnit. Eccleſ.</hi> declareth how the Church <hi>was knowne by Scriptures,</hi> and not by thoſe falſe Markes which the Pope and his Supporters thruſt vpon it. By Scripture alſo wee plainely diſcerne, that the Apoſtate and his fellowes are a packe of wicked Heretikes and Schiſmatikes, and no Communion of Saints, or Catholike Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Donatists</hi> denyed the vniuerſalitie of the Church, and ſayd it was periſhed in all places ſaue in <hi>Afrike,</hi> and in the Communion of the <hi>Donatiſts.</hi> S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> therefore diſputing againſt them, confoundeth this Rinegate and his Apoſtaticall fellowes, who confine the Church within the Limits of the Popes Dioceſſe, and Territories of the <hi>Roman</hi> Obedience, holding it to be fallen and vaniſhed away in all other places. As for vs, we neyther denie the Church to be vniuerſall, nor hold, that <hi>Christs Catholike Church can periſh or faile,</hi> although this ſhameleſſe Companion doth impoſe this Error vpon vs; whom he maliciouſly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>Caluiniſts</hi> and <hi>Lutherans,</hi> foming out his rage againſt his Parents, Friends, and Countreymen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the true viſible Church is Judge of Controuerſies, and cannot poſsibly erre,</hi> is not any Doctrine of S. <hi>Auguſtines.</hi> but an abſurd Error of this Rinegate. For firſt, eyther the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:238:30"/>Church iudgeth her owne Controuerſies, and ſo ſitteth Iudge in her owne Cauſe; or the Cauſes of Strangers and Infidels, who will not heare her Sentence. Secondly, S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> neuer appealed to the Pope, but to <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. Thirdly, neuer doth the Church meet, to iudge any mans Cauſe; nor ought Biſhops to iudge otherwiſe, then according to holy Scriptures, <hi>iuxta Legem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eius,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſayth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. Fourthly, the Church of <hi>Afrike,</hi> of which S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>contr. Epiſt. Fundam. c.</hi> 5. is not now viſible, nor extant in the World. Fiftly, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth not, becauſe the Church <hi>moued him to beleeue the Goſpel,</hi> that therefore the ſame is ſupreme Iudge: for any man or woman may induce a man to beleeue the Goſpel, yet euery one is not a ſupreme and infallible Iudge. Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Church of <hi>Epheſus, Corinth,</hi> and <hi>Galatia,</hi> was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time a true viſible Church, and yet it is now fayled, and ſubiect to groſſe Errors, and neuer was the ſupreme Iudge of matters of Faith. Neyther is it materiall, <hi>that the Truth remaineth in the Belly of the Church,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſayth in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57. for the Truth remained in the Church of the <hi>Coloſſians, Theſſalonians,</hi> and <hi>Philippians,</hi> yet neyther were theſe Churches ſupreme Iudges, nor did they alwayes abide in Truth: and whatſoeuer wee thinke of them, yet the Truth abideth not alwayes in the Head, Belly, Legges, or Chayre of the Pope.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If any feare to be deceiued,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>con. Creſc. c.</hi> 33. <hi>let him conſult the Church, which without doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe the holy Scripture doth demonſtrate.</hi> And therein we willingly follow his aduice, conſulting the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> But the Aduerſaries doe contrarie, conſult the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of <hi>Rome,</hi> compoſed of Popes, Cardinals, Inquiſitors, Woluiſh Prelates, Maſſe-Prieſts, Monkes, Fryars, Nunnes, and ignorant people, knowing nothing of the Faith, which neyther Scriptures nor Fathers demonſtrate, vnleſſe it be in <hi>Babylon, Apocalypſe</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>He ſayth further, <hi>that no man can be ſaued, but in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:238:31"/>Church:</hi> and ſo ſay wee. But wee denie the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of <hi>Rome,</hi> deſpiſing holy Scriptures, and adulterating the Doctrine of Sacraments, giuen vs by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to be that Church. They may pretend to be Catholikes, as other Heretikes doe, and ſing <hi>Alleluia, De Profundis, Aue Sancta Crux,</hi> and <hi>Salue: Regina;</hi> but out of the Catholike and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike Church, as they hold, the new Creed of <hi>Trent,</hi> and Doctrine of Schooles, they cannot be ſaued. Greaſed and ſalued they may bee, but ſaued they cannot be.</p>
               <p>And hereof he bringeth another reaſon, <hi>De vnit. Eccleſ. c.</hi> 16. becauſe they <hi>haue not Christ for their head,</hi> and this is proued becauſe they haue the Pope for their head; nay, they haue <hi>Antichriſt</hi> for their head. They alſo hold the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies of the <hi>Simonians,</hi> and <hi>Carpocratians, Angelikes, Colly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridians; Nudipedales. Manichees,</hi> and <hi>Pelagians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The bookes of <hi>Tobia, Judith, Wiſdome, Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> and the <hi>Machabees,</hi> S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> neuer made equall to the Law and Prophets. Nay, he denyeth them to haue beene repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Canonicall by the Church before <hi>Christ,</hi> albeit in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard they contayned Precepts of manners they were read in the Church, and in a generall ſignification might be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Canonicall.</p>
               <p>Of S. <hi>Peters</hi> primacie, this prime Diſciple of <hi>Antichrist</hi> hath little reaſon to prate. For firſt, S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> giueth him no command or ſuperioritie ouer the Apoſtles, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a prime Place in order in reſpect of his feruor, Age and Vertue. Secondly, hee had no power to depoſe Princes, or to make Lawes; This belonged to the Councell, that, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to any Apoſtle, nor any Councell. Thirdly, the Pope neyther feedeth <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſheepe, nor loueth <hi>Chriſt;</hi> nay, he is more like to <hi>Nero,</hi> then to <hi>Peter.</hi> Fourthly, the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> had no Apoſtolicall Prerogatiue, nor had they power ouer Scriptures, mens Conſciences, Princes or all other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. Laſtly, the Biſhops of <hi>Afrike,</hi> and among others S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> thought themſelues in no degree inferiour to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:238:31"/>
               <p>S. <hi>Auſtine, contr. part. Donat.</hi> where hee ſpeaketh of the Rock, againſt which the proud gates of Hell cannot preuaile, vnderſtandeth S. <hi>Peters</hi> Confeſſion and Doctrine, and not the ſucceſſion of Popes, as this Popelin would haue it. For, againſt <hi>Marcellinus</hi> the gates of Hell preuayled, and no ſtrength is there in the Succeſſion of the reſt. Secondly; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth hee call S. <hi>Peters</hi> feat an Epiſcopall feat of <hi>Peter,</hi> as this falſe Tranſlator hath turned it, but onely an order of Biſhops, <hi>In ordine illo Patrum, quis cui ſucceſſit videte,</hi> are his wordes. Thirdly, hee doth ſignifie, that other Biſhops were as well Succeſſors of <hi>Peter</hi> as the Biſhops of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To end this point concerning his Judgement of the Church and the viſible head thereof,</hi> ſaith this viſible and palpable Sot, as if S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> had euer taught, that the Pope was the viſible head of the Church, or that his Decrees and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations were the determination of the Church. What a brainleſſe head and brazen face hath the Apoſtate to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme this?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſucceſſion of Prieſts,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine, kept him in the Church.</hi> But not the <hi>perſonall Succeſſion of them,</hi> nor the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Popes, as this Rinegate impudently affirmeth. Further vntill S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> time the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Succeſſours of <hi>Peter</hi> continued in the Catholike Faith. But now the <hi>Popes</hi> are Apoſtated from the Faith, and haue abandoned the office of Biſhops; profeſſing new Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and aſſuming to them a new Office.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auſtine De anim. &amp; ejus Orig. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. beleeued not, <hi>That Iufants dying without Baptiſme could obtaine remiſſion of originall ſinne.</hi> But neyther hee, nor the Schoole-men ſay, that all not Baptiſed are neceſſarily damned, holding, that beſide the baptiſme of Water, there is a baptiſme of Blood, and of the Holy Ghoſt. S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> doubted not of the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of <hi>Valentinian,</hi> albeit hee dyed vnbaptiſed. And the ſame is the opinion of the vnbaptiſed and beleeuing Thiefe, and ſuch Martyrs as ſhed their blood for CHRIST.</p>
               <p>For the Popiſh reall and externall Sacrifice of the Maſſe,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:238:32"/>S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſpeaketh no one word, howſoeuer it pleaſeth this ſlaue of Antichriſt to vouch him for it. He doth not ſo much as once name the Maſſe, or ſay that <hi>Chriſts</hi> Body was really offered vnder the accidents of Bread and Wine. The ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice he ſpeaketh of, was onely a memoriall of the ſacrifice of <hi>Chriſts</hi> death; and <hi>Monica</hi> was onely remembred at the Altar, as other Chriſtians, Patriarkes, and Martyrs were, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit her ſoule was not in Purgatorie.</p>
               <p>Papiſts alſo build Churches to Martyrs and Saints, and call vpon them, contrarie to the Doctrine of S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 22. <hi>de Ciuit. Dei, c.</hi> 10. who albeit they were named in the Myſteries, yet denyeth that eyther they were called vpon, or had Temples built vnto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 17. <hi>de Ciuit. Dei, c.</hi> 20. hee admitteth none to be Prieſts <hi>after the Order of</hi> Melchiſedech, <hi>or Mediators of the New Teſtament, but</hi> CHRIST IESVS: <hi>Sacerdos ipſe Noui Teſtamenti, &amp; ſecundum Ordinem Melchiſedech.</hi> But this Apoſtate ſuppoſeth, that his Maſſe-Prieſts are after the Order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> and that Saints canonized by the Pope, are Mediators of the New Teſtament, albeit neyther New nor Old Teſtament was eſtabliſhed in their bloud.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We adore Chriſts fleſh,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> allegorically ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the words of the 98. <hi>Pſalme:</hi> but not <hi>in the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries,</hi> as this Patron of the Myſterie of Iniquitie affirmeth; nor doth he ſpeake of <hi>the Sacrifice of the Maſſe,</hi> as this Dreamer imagineth: for he ſpeaketh of the ſpirituall eating of <hi>Chriſts</hi> fleſh, that is adored when it is beleeued, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually receiued by Faith. That <hi>Chriſts</hi> fleſh was vnder the accidents of Bread and Wine, and really contained in the Prieſts hands, neyther did S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> or other Fathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue; for that were nothing elſe then to betray <hi>Chriſt;</hi> as did <hi>Judas,</hi> into the hands of Theeues. That <hi>Chriſts</hi> Body is to be eaten with the mouth, he vtterly denyeth: <hi>Non hoc corpus quod videtis mandueaturi eſtis,</hi> ſayth he.</p>
               <p>Againe, in <hi>Conc.</hi> 1. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 33. expounding theſe words, <hi>Ferebatur in manibus ſuis,</hi> he vnderſtandeth them of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:238:32"/>in <hi>Chriſts</hi> hands; for ſpeaking properly, he ſayth, <hi>No man is carryed in his owne hands:</hi> which words the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facioner eyther marked not, or wilfully diffembled.</p>
               <p>Prayers for the dead, inferre not the Doctrine of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie; as the place of the 2. <hi>Machab.</hi> 12. albeit corrupted, and his Booke <hi>de cura pro Mortuis,</hi> doth declare: for ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he there mention any Purgatorie, nor did he euer thinke, that his Mothers ſoule was in Purgatorie. In <hi>Enchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid. ad Lament.</hi> hee ſpeaketh of purging ſmall faults, but very doubtingly: but that Chriſtians were to ſatisfie in Purgatorie for ſinnes, whoſe guilt was remitted, hee neuer taught nor imagined. <hi>Aërius</hi> was condemned as an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> relateth <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 53. <hi>de Haereſ. ad Quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uultd.</hi> but it was becauſe he was an <hi>Arrian.</hi> He was repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued alſo for denying, not <hi>Sacrifices and Prayers for the Dead,</hi> as this Apoſtate, lying moſt deadly and impudently, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, but a Commemoration for the Dead, then vſed, wherein Martyrs and holy Saints were mentioned. As for the Sacrifice, 2. <hi>Machab.</hi> 12. it will profit the Apoſtate but little, being offered for the Damned.</p>
               <p>In his ſecond Sermon vpon the 88. <hi>Pſalme.</hi> S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> would haue <hi>Saints Feaſts celebrated with ſobrietie.</hi> But what maketh that for innocation of Saints, or celebrating Maſſes in their honour? Further, theſe words ſeeme to be patched to the end of the Pſalme by ſome idle Monke, that was zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for his Belly, and more willing to feaſt then faſt: for neyther haue they any connexion with the words going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, nor was it the vſe to celebrate Feaſts in S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> dayes for other Saints then Martyrs, as appeareth <hi>Lib.</hi> 20. <hi>contra Fauſt. c.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>That S. <hi>Auſtine proued Prayers to Saints and Angels out of Scriptures,</hi> is a moſt groſſe Vntruth, vttered by a lying Apoſtate. In the 21. Booke <hi>de Ciuit. Dei, c.</hi> 27. alledged by him, is no ſuch matter ſound: Nay, in the 22. Booke <hi>de Ciuit. c.</hi> 10. he condemneth the inuocation of Martyrs. And <hi>Lib.</hi> 10. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 42. <hi>&amp;</hi> 43. ſheweth, that the Office of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:238:33"/>Reconciliation and Mediation betweene God and man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to <hi>Chriſt</hi> onely, and not to Angels or Saints.</p>
               <p>In the 22. Booke de <hi>Ciuit. Dei, c.</hi> 8. diuers Miracles are reported, as <hi>wrought ſome by holy Earth, ſome by Reliques, and ſome by other meanes.</hi> But the whole Diſcourſe ſauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth rather of the Veine of ſome Monke, or writer of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gends, then of ſo learned and graue a Father. Howbeit, whoſoeuer is the Author of that Addition, he neyther men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth the Maſſe, nor inuocation or prayers to Saints, for which by the Apoſtate it is vainely alledged; nor ſayth, that Miracles were wrought by ſuch ſuperſtitious Tricks.</p>
               <p>In his Booke <hi>de Grat. &amp; Lib. Arb. c.</hi> 16. he ſayth, <hi>It is certaine we keepe Gods Commandements, if we will.</hi> But he ſayth not, it is in the power of the will to keepe Gods Commandements, or as the Apoſtate inferreth, that <hi>man hath poſſibilitie to keepe Gods Commandements:</hi> For preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the holy Father addeth, <hi>That our will must be prepared of the Lord, and that we can doe nothing, vnleſſe it be giuen vs of God.</hi> Further, to hold that man by his will can fulfill the Law of God, is <hi>Pelagianiſme. Lib. de Nat. &amp; Grat. c.</hi> 43. <hi>Wee must,</hi> as he counſelleth vs, <hi>demand grace of God, that we may doe that which we cannot otherwiſe.</hi> But what need Grace, if the Will had power ſufficient to doe well?</p>
               <p>In his firſt Booke of <hi>Retract. c.</hi> 21. S. <hi>Austine</hi> doth vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ouerthrow the Popiſh Doctrine, concerning the power of Free-will, in doing good: For <hi>if man cannot change his will, vnleſſe it be giuen him, nor doe good but by grace,</hi> as hee teacheth, then doth it not lye in the power of Free-will to doe well, more then it lyeth in the power of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate to be made a Cardinall: which is a grace beſtowed by the Pope on his fauourites, and not obtained by euery looſe companions free-will.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Austine</hi> doth alſo confound the Hereſie of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, holding iuſtification by Faith and Workes; for <hi>if Workes follow him that is iustified, and goe not before,</hi> then doe not Workes iuſtifie vs. Yet hold we not, that Faith de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:238:33"/>of Workes doth iuſtifie, but that Faith liuely by good Workes doth onely apprehend <hi>Chriſts</hi> Mercy and luſtice, and not our Workes effect Iuſtice.</p>
               <p>That S. <hi>Auſtine, with other Fathers of the Church</hi> teach, <hi>that our Workes are meritorious of Eternall life,</hi> as this Apoſtate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoweth, is an impudent aſſertion diſauowed by them, and meritorious of a ſharp cenſure. S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> neither in his 105. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> nor in his 46. <hi>Epiſt. ad Valent.</hi> doth in one word ſignifie that Workes are meritorious of Eternal life. Nay contrary, albeit he doth mention Merits: yet, he ſaith, <hi>men are juſtified by Grace without merits.</hi> Which ouerthroweth the Doctrine of Merites <hi>de congruo,</hi> and the Decrees of <hi>Trent</hi> concerning mens preparations to Iuſtice. <hi>Jn Epiſt.</hi> 46. <hi>ad Valent.</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Man is conuerted by mercy &amp; grace.</hi> In <hi>Conc.</hi> 2. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 36. he denieth our Workes <hi>to be meritorious of that we ſhall receiue.</hi> And in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83. <hi>That what ſoeuer he hath promiſed, he promiſed to ſuch as are vnworthy.</hi> And <hi>Ser.</hi> 16. <hi>de verb. Apoſt. He is made our debtor,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>not receiuing anything from vs, but promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing what pleaſed him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus it appeareth, that S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> is little propitious to Papiſts euen in thoſe points, in which they thinke him to be moſt fauourable. But their maine grounds hee eyther knew not or contradicted them, as hath been formerly demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Moſt idle therefore is his whole Diſcourſe enſuing.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>he wondreth, that any ſhould be ſo ſilly or impudent,</hi> as <hi>to auouch S.</hi> Auſtine <hi>as a Patron of the Faith which wee profeſſe,</hi> whom he like a Calfe of the <hi>Popes</hi> Buls calleth <hi>Caluiniſts.</hi> But I haue alledged againſt him ſo many particulars, that I hope he will ceaſe his wonderment. I haue alſo deriued our. Faith from <hi>Chriſt</hi> &amp; his Apoſtles, and not from <hi>Caluin</hi> or any late teacher. S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> argued <hi>againſt the</hi> Manichies, <hi>that held Fate,</hi> and <hi>the</hi> Pelagians, <hi>that magnified Free-will, and made an Idoll of it.</hi> But what doth that concerne vs, who deteſt all the Hereſies both of the one and the other. It rather toucheth the Apoſtate and his conſorts, who according to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Thomas,</hi> 1. <hi>P. q.</hi> 116. <hi>Art.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. allow Fate, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:238:34"/>with the <hi>Manichies</hi> condemne Mariage in Prieſts, and giue to CHRIST a phantaſticall body, that is in many places at one time, and refuſe Fleſh and other meates. They alſo mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie Free-will as being the Cauſe of mans conuerſion, and hauing power to prepare vs to Iuſtification; and hold, that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> and ſome others, were borne without Originall ſinne, and that Iuſt men may liue without ſinne for ſome time, and the vniuſt doe any good by their Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will: all which, are Hereſies of the <hi>Pelagians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He addeth, that S. <hi>Auſtine, beleeued the inuocation of Saints and Angels to bee a Catholike Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>that hee,</hi> did <hi>not onely approue Prayers made to Saints, but alſo recounteth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Miracles wrought by them:</hi> Lyes idly repeated, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly refured. See S. <hi>Auſtines Confeſ. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 42. <hi>&amp;</hi> 43. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 22 <hi>de ciuit. Dei, c.</hi> 10. and you ſhall finde hee teacheth contrary. The miracles reported, <hi>Lib.</hi> 22. <hi>de ciuit. c.</hi> 8. are thruſt in there by ſome falſary; and yet is it not there ſayd, they were wrought by Saints.</p>
               <p>He ſuppoſeth, <hi>that wee inferre that Scriptures containe all things neceſſary to ſaluation; becauſe,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>lib. Confeſ. &amp;. c.</hi> 5. <hi>they are excellent meanes whereby God may hee both beleeued and ſerued,</hi> But his ſuppoſall is ridiculous and falſe; for neyther hath S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> in that place any ſuch words, nor doe we ground our ſelues vpon any thing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained, but vpon diuers other place, <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de doctr. Christ. c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Tract.</hi> 49. <hi>in Joan. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de couſenſ. Euangel. c.</hi> 35. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>centr. lib. Petil. c.</hi> 6. and <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cantr. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s epiſt. Pelag. c.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Farre hee was,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtate, <hi>from holding Scripture to hee the ſupriame Iudge of Controuerſies;</hi> Yes, <hi>lib</hi> 3. <hi>de Nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>. c.</hi> 33. hee appealeth to <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtle. He doth alſo try all queſtione in all place by Scriptures, and no where by the <hi>Pope</hi> or his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. That <hi>the Goſpell with h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n had beene no Goſpell, if the authority of the Church had not obliged him?</hi> is a wicked ſpeech of this blaſphemous A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſtate, and no ſaying of S. <hi>Auſtine.</hi> Hee ſaid onely the Authority of the Church moued him, which hee might
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:238:34"/>haue affirmed of any godly Preacher, yea, of his Mother.</p>
               <p>If S. <hi>Auſtines,</hi> or other Fathers words ſeeme to fauour vs, the Rinegate pretendeth, <hi>That ſo many other places are plaine and expreſſe for his Romiſh Religion; inſomuch, that ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe they contradict themſelues.</hi> Both groſſe and impudent leaſings; For the firſt, we haue refuted by many vnanſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble arguments: the ſecond, hee cannot chuſe but confeſſe, vnleſſe he can produce ſuch as charge the Fathers with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions.</p>
               <p>But ſaith he, <hi>The</hi> Roman <hi>Church hath preſerued S.</hi> Auſtines <hi>Workes vntouched:</hi> ſecondly, <hi>ſhee preſerued two Orders of Religious men inſtituted by him:</hi> thirdly, <hi>ſhee permitted his Images and Reliques to bee kept and honoured, his Feſtiuall to bee ſolemnized, and Churches and Altars to bee erected to God in his name.</hi> I anſwer, that the firſt is moſt vntrue; for the Popes factors haue not onely added to his Workes many ſuppoſitious Bookes, but alſo haue falſified his true works; and if any ſinceritie haue beene vſed in the edition of his writings, it is much againſt the Popes minde. But ſuppoſe the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> ſhould haue vſed diligence in preſeruing his Writings, yet is not the ſame comparable to the diligence of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> in preſeruing the Old Teſtament, by which notwithſtanding they are plainly conuinced. 2. It is falſe, that eyther Hermites or Chanons regular were inſtituted by S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> they hauing receiued their Originall and Lawes from the Pope. 3. The <hi>Jewes</hi> honored the Prophets, albeit, they regarded not their admonitions and counſailes. 4. It is guibriſh to ſay, <hi>that Churches and Altars were built to God in S.</hi> Auſtines <hi>name;</hi> for S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Church is built to Saint <hi>Auſtine,</hi> as <hi>Baals</hi> Church to <hi>Baal.</hi> 5. Not Gods Church, but the Sinagogue of <hi>Sathan</hi> maintaineth the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous worſhip of Saints, of their Reliques and Images.</p>
               <p>He ſaith, <hi>wee diſclaime S.</hi> Auſtine, <hi>and call him ſuperſtitious, and ſcornefully trample vpon the head and heart of this glorious Saint.</hi> But would he diſclayme his lying and calumniating, this accuſation would ſoone ceaſe. To preferre holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:238:35"/>before any one Father, is no ſcorne nor wrong. <hi>Caluin</hi> in ſome things leaueth him; but Papiſts leaue him where he followeth the Apoſtle, and ſetteth forth the grace of <hi>Christ:</hi> they beleeue, that <hi>Monicaes</hi> ſoule was in Purgatorie; but ſo did not S. <hi>Auſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Toward the end of his Preface, hauing almoſt tyred him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with lying, and buſie ſearch of that he cannot finde, he cryeth out, <hi>O Hereſie, how deepe are thy Rootes layd in Hell!</hi> Some pang belike of Helliſh Treaſon and Hereſie wrung his rotten carkaſſe, and pinched him at the heart: for to denie Maſſes and Dirges for the dead, is no Hereſie; but to deſtroy <hi>Chriſts</hi> humanitie, to renounce his grace, and to maintaine <hi>Pelagianiſme,</hi> as Papiſts doe, is moſt groſſe and notorious Hereſie.</p>
               <p>We eſteeme S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> and other Fathers, as much as they deſire to be eſteemed, and preferre them farre before the Pope and his whole Conſiſtorie of Cardinals. But the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts doe preferre euery blind and ignorant Popes Sentence before all the ancient Fathers: of whom, albeit they ſpeake gloriouſly in their Breuiaries and Miſſals, yet they neyther regard them, nor the Apoſtles of our Sauiour, if they ſpeake againſt their holy Father, and his profit, and Monkes ſlow bellyes.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> beleeued, repented, and liued a boly life: but yet he neyther whipped himſelfe, nor <hi>did Penance,</hi> as Fryars do; neyther did he make boaſt of <hi>his eminencie in all perfection of life,</hi> which the Apoſtate attributeth vnto him. The Fable of the writing of the ſeuen <hi>Penitentiall Pſalmes</hi> before S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> as he lay on dying, is not probable; the ſame being a practiſe of Fryars, and not mentioned by <hi>Poſſidonius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We endeuor by Faith and good Workes, and the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of a good Conſcience, to make our election ſure to vs; and ſo no doubt, did S. <hi>Auſtine:</hi> but <hi>we perſwade no man to aſſure himſelfe of his ſaluation, his life being flagitious and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall, and himſelfe being ignorant, and liuing without repentance, and hauing Faith onely, without good Workes,</hi> as this lying and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:238:35"/>flagitious Apoſtate doth falſely charge vs; that is rather the flagitious error of the Apoſtate and his Conſorts, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſaluation to all abſolued by Maſſe-Prieſts, and dying in the Popes Faith: which was alſo the Hereſie of <hi>Eunomius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The example of</hi> S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> he ſayth, <hi>is profitable to all men, whether they be in ſtate of puritie, or are fallen into ſenſualitie, hauing darke and frozen ſoules.</hi> As if S. <hi>Austine</hi> were a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharist,</hi> or <hi>Puritan;</hi> or ſenſuall Papiſts, whoſe hearts are darkened with ignorance, and frozen with coldneſſe of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, could reape any profit by S. <hi>Austines</hi> example.</p>
               <p>Onely he would not haue <hi>his Reader ſo to remember S.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, <hi>as to forget their deuotion to his Mother</hi> Monica; <hi>who,</hi> as he ſayth, <hi>had a manly ſoule, indued with maſſie and ſolide vertues.</hi> A note of remembrance, full of ſtoliditie rather then ſoliditie: for deuotion and religion, in the opinion of all ſolide Chriſtians, tryeth vs to God, and not to men or women departed this life, and vnknowne to vs. Further, if her ſoule were manly, why may not the Apoſtate haue a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male ſoule, being ſo much addicted to the feminine gender? If her vertues were maſſie, why may not his vanities be ſpongeous and light, like Tyffanie? Laſtly, if S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> and his Mother were Saints, being not canonized by the Pope; then is the Popes power, lately vſurped in canonizing Saints, nothing. And thus an end of the Apoſtates idle and long Preface: proface to his indignitie, that hath thus vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily diſgraced himſelfe, and his graceleſſe Cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Notes and Aduertiſements vpon the Tranſlators Aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, concerning S. <hi>AVSTINES</hi> Retractations.</head>
               <p>ALthough his idle Aduertiſement to the Reader, is neyther worth any Animaduerſion, nor the Readers paines; yet becauſe it commeth in ſute next after his Preface, it followeth in order, that vpon his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſement, we put our Animaduerſions.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:238:36"/>
               <p>And firſt, I could not ouerpaſſe his impudence and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, albeit noted before, in calling himſelfe and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions Catholikes, whoſe Faith is neyther Catholike, nor Apoſtolike, nor Chriſtian. Let him, if he haue any ſhame, demonſtrate, that <hi>Chriſts</hi> Body is made of Bread, nay, of Wine, and that it is contained vnder the accidents of Bread and Wine, and was eaten not onely by the Apoſtles, but alſo by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, yea, by men and beaſts, eating the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that the Pope is <hi>Chriſts</hi> Vicar, and hath two Swords, and power to depoſe and kill Kings; that Fryars and Monks were inſtituted by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and liue in <hi>perfect puritie;</hi> and all the new Creed of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When we are vrged by Papiſts <hi>with the authoritie of Saint</hi> Auſtine, <hi>making euidently againſt vs, it is our vſe,</hi> ſayth the Aduertiſer, <hi>to alledge, that he made Bookes of Retractation.</hi> But firſt, he is not able to ſhew any authoritie of S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> making euidently againſt vs: contrariwiſe, we haue alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged places making euidently againſt the Popiſh Faction and their Hereſies. Secondly, it is no fault to ſay, he made Books of Retractations. Thirdly, wee alledge places neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted. Laſtly, it is an eaſie matter to auoid whatſoeuer is obiected againſt vs out of S. <hi>Austine,</hi> without any ſuch fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous and idle ſhift, as is by this poore ſhifter ſuggeſted and deuiſed for vs.</p>
               <p>Where S. <hi>Austine, Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 13. ſpeaketh <hi>of the price of our Redemption,</hi> he ſayth, <hi>nothing is ſignified, but the Sacrifice of the Maſſe.</hi> A conceit fond and ridiculous: for firſt, what is more abſurd, then to confeſſe, that the ſoule of the Tranſlator and his companions is of ſo little value, that they may be redeemed with euery three-halfe-peny Maſſe? Secondly, that Father doth not ſo much as in one word men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Sacrifice of the Maſſe. Thirdly, hee vnderſtandeth the Sacrifice made vpon the Croſſe, for our Redemption; a memoriall whereof is made in the holy Myſteries, propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by wicked Maſſe-Prieſts.</p>
               <p>That which S. <hi>Austine</hi> ſayth of Prayers for the Dead,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:238:36"/>maketh nothing eyther for the ſale of Maſſes, or Dirges, or the blazing fire of Purgatorie: neyther is the Apoſtate able to auow his irreligion by any words of S. <hi>Austine,</hi> of Vowes, of Miracles, or of the darkeneſſe of any Texts of Scriptures.</p>
               <p>He telleth vs, that S. <hi>Austine</hi> mentioneth <hi>Monaſteries of Religious perſons, and great numbers of Hermites:</hi> yet cannot he ſhew any ſuch inſtitation of Hermites, nor demonſtrate, that S. <hi>Austine</hi> euer knew any Popiſh Monke or Fryar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That one and the ſame Scripture hath very many and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſences,</hi> is not the Doctrine of S. <hi>Austine,</hi> but the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh conceit of this idle Tranſlator, that hath in his head very many crotchets, but very little ſence or vnderſtanding: for how can we be aſſured of the truth and certaine vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Scriptures; if the ſame haue many ſences? <hi>Apollo Loxias</hi> gaue forth ambiguous Oracles; but farre is that from the Text of holy Scriptures, and the wiſdome of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>He noteth alſo, that <hi>albeit S.</hi> Auſtine <hi>wrote the ſtorie of his youth, yet he was no young man when he wrote his Booke.</hi> A high point of the Tranſlators learning; as if old men could not write the ſtorie of their younger yeeres: the Tranſlator him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, if he pleaſe, may write what he did in the Brothels of <hi>France, Italy,</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> when he was younger then now.</p>
               <p>Further he chargeth vs, as if we ſhould ſay, <hi>that S.</hi> Auſtine <hi>was but a young man when he wrote his Confeſſions, and that afterward he grew wiſer.</hi> As if any of vs did taxe S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> of indiſcretion, for writing this Booke: if he know any ſuch, why doth he-not name them? if he name none, himſelfe ſeemeth to be a falſe accuſer; who albeit growne in yeeres, is neyther more honeſt, nor wiſe, then when he was young.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He in his Retractations,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>confeſſed his ſinnes and good deeds.</hi> An example which the Aduertiſer meaneth not to follow: for his enormious ſinnes he will not confeſſe, and good deeds I know none he hath to relate.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:238:37"/>
               <p>He addeth, that <hi>his Confeſſions much pleaſed many of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> Yet we heare of no Confeſſion, that this prodigall, and Popiſh Apoſtate hath made, nor doth he greatly care to pleaſe his Parents, Brethren and Friends; neyther doth his Tranſlation pleaſe any man, but himſelfe.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> in his fourth Booke of <hi>Confeſſions,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hee made rather a light Declamation, then a ſerious Confeſſion.</hi> But the aduertiſer although hee make both idle Declamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and friuolous and falſe Annotations, yet neyther in jeſt nor earneſt doth hee confeſſe his faults, but rather proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vaine-gloriouſly boaſt of his doings.</p>
               <p>In the end the Aduertiſer beſeecheth <hi>his diſcreet Reader to admire the humility and exactneſſe of the Saint.</hi> A requeſt that concerneth himſelfe nothing, that is neither Saint, nor hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor exact, nor diſcreet; nay, fooliſhly hee admireth himſelfe and his doings, albeit, his Prefaces, Notes and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſements, containe nothing but foolery, vanity and lyes.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> ſaith the Aduertiſer, <hi>beleeued what hee taught.</hi> But neyther did hee teach any thing in fauour of his Popiſh Hereſies, nor preiudiciall to the Faith of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Vainely hee boaſteth that the moderne Faith of <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>Catholike;</hi> But we haue conuinced it to be neither Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, nor Apoſtolike, nor true. Let him anſwer to our argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and hee ſhall be forced to confeſſe ſo much himſelfe.</p>
               <p>This aduertiſement therefore, howſoeuer it pleaſed the Tranſlator therein to mention S. Auſtines <hi>Retractations,</hi> maketh nothing for his owne glory and commendation. He ſhould haue ſhewed more wiſedome, if hee had retracted both his Preface and Aduertiſement.</p>
               <p>After his Aduitiſement he confeſſeth, that <hi>his Copie was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill written,</hi> and <hi>that many errours eſcaped in Printing.</hi> But this ſhould eaſily haue beene pardoned, if that his whole la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour had beene well performed, and groſſe Errours had not been committed in his Preface, Annotations and Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Now then wee come to ſpeake of his Annotations and Tranſlations reſerued for the laſt Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:238:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of the falſe, wicked, and abſurd Annotations of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate vpon S. <hi>AVGVSTINES</hi> Confeſſions, and how euill-fauouredly they and hee anſwere the Text.</head>
               <p>SAint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in the firſt Booke of his <hi>Confeſſions, Cap.</hi> 2. Doth inuocate his <hi>Lord and God, which made Heauen and Earth:</hi> and which notwithſtanding <hi>was not contayned in them.</hi> But this Apoſtate and his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes doth inuocate and call vpon Angels and Saints; yea, vpon their God of the Altar, that neither made Heauen nor Earth, nor any thing elſe, but as themſelues ſay, was made by a Prieſt, and is contayned vnder the accidents of Bread and Wine, and ſhut vp in a Pixe, and hanged ouer the Altar. This the Apoſtate did well perceiue, made not for his profit; and therefore hee was content to paſſe by this Chapter in ſad ſilence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Supererogatur tibi vti debeas,</hi> which the Apoſtate tranſlateth thus: <hi>By our Supererogation thou becommeſt our debtor;</hi> and noteth, that God <hi>maketh vs able to doe workes of Supererogation.</hi> But neyther doth that holy Father ſay, or thinke, that God was made our debtor for our Workes, but onely for his Promiſe, nor account Monkiſh vowes to be workes of Supererogation, nor teach, that man was able to performe the whole Law and more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. the Tranſlator noteth, <hi>That S.</hi> Auſtine <hi>did oblige God to bee good vnto him.</hi> A patch ſtitched to the Text and not in one word ſignified by that holy Father, and moſt falſe. For by what obligation can God, that is aboue all, be obliged to a ſinfull man, that is ſo farre vnderneath him? Nay, in this very Chapter hee <hi>declareth his ſinnes against himſelfe,</hi> and confeſſing <hi>the impietie of his</hi> heart, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming his Merites and Workes, ſaith, <hi>Hee will not ſtand in judgement with God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Margent, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. the Tranſlator noteth, <hi>that
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:238:38"/>there are Sectaries who blaſphemouſly affirme, that God appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth men to ſinne.</hi> But he durſt not name any party, leaſt tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching M. <hi>Caluin,</hi> he ſhould be deprehended in a manifeſt Lye, and conuinced of his ordinarie Crime of Calumniati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Howbeit, if men ſhould appoint men to worſhip the Pope, and to embrace his Hereſies; to worſhip Saints and Images, after the practiſe of <hi>Rome;</hi> to rebell againſt Princes excommunicated by the Pope, which the Apoſtaticall Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Rome</hi> ſayth he doth; then by their Doctrine he ſhould appoint men indeed to ſinne. Wee ſay, onely God forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all ſinnes, and directeth all mens actions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. he obſerueth <hi>the vſe of ſigning with the Croſſe:</hi> but S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> there ſpeaketh of ſigning and ſalting Infants newly come out of their Mothers Wombe, and ſometime before Baptiſme; Ceremonies not now vſed in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church. Hee talketh therefore of no matters of Faith, nor helpeth the Tranſlator, who ſo often and ſuperſtitiouſly abuſeth that ſigne.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auſtine, Chap.</hi> 13. toucheth the <hi>buyers and ſellers of Grammar:</hi> but the Tranſlator addeth <hi>Rules,</hi> as if Rules of Grammar were ſold, ſo that a man might haue licence to ſpeake falſe <hi>Latine.</hi> In <hi>Rome</hi> the Pope ſelleth Rules, Lawes, and Diſpenſations; but the Tranſlator careth for none of that, nor doth the Pope care for Grammar Rules, or good <hi>Latine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16. S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſpeaketh of <hi>a Floud:</hi> but the Tranſlator turneth it <hi>into a Torrent,</hi> and noteth in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, <hi>A noble Diſcourſe;</hi> as if it were a noble thing to talke of <hi>Torrents of Cuſtome,</hi> and <hi>drying vp of Flouds.</hi> Afterward he talketh of learning theſe words, <hi>the Golden Shower, the Lap, the Ornament, and the Temple of Heauen;</hi> and the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator noteth <hi>an extreme abuſe ſtill on foot,</hi> but ſheweth not what it is, nor wherein it conſiſteth. Theſe words, <hi>Qui tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla Coeli ſummo ſonitu conculit,</hi> he tranſlateth thus, <hi>which ſhakes the whole Vault of Heauen with his ſoueraigne Voyce:</hi> as if the Heauen were like a Vault of a Cellar, and euery great
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:238:38"/>noyſe were a ſoueraigne Voyce. O the ſoueraigne dizardrie of a tranſcendent Tranſlator, whoſe words ſoare aboue all vnderſtanding and reaſon!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God is the Centre of all true ſweetneſſe,</hi> ſayth the Apoſtate in a Marginall Note vpon the firſt Chapter of the ſecond Booke of <hi>Confeſſions.</hi> But in the Text there is no mention of Centre, or Circumference: neyther is God in the loweſt place, as a Centre, but filleth all things with his preſence. And where S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>Exarſi aliquando ſatiari in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feris in adoleſcentia,</hi> he turneth it thus; <hi>I did ſometimes burne with a kind of helliſh deſire, to be ſatisfied:</hi> as if Hell were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but helliſh deſires.</p>
               <p>And commenting vpon the ſecond Booke, and ſecond Chapter, he ſayth in his Marginall Note, <hi>That Virginitie is a better diſpoſition to receiue Diuine conſolation, then the ſtate of Marriage.</hi> But S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> talketh nothing of this diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; nor do Popiſh Votaries, that forſweare Marriage, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther attaine to perfect chaſtitie, or receiue the Diuine conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations he ſpeaketh of: nay, <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob, Moſes,</hi> and other marryed men, receiued more conſolations from God, then all the packe of vnmarryed Popes, Monkes, and Fryars.</p>
               <p>Theſe words, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Et volutabur in caeno eius, tanquam in Cinamomis &amp; Vnguentis praetioſis,</hi> he tranſlated thus; <hi>And I weltred in the myre thereof, as if I had beene regaled in a Bed of Spices and precious Odours:</hi> as if there were no Spices but Cinamon, and Oyntment did ſignifie Odours. Would he not be anoynted with Hogs-dung for corrupting the Text, and baſtonaded with a Ruler, which maketh an <hi>Engliſh</hi> word of a <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> and thruſteth it into the Tranſlation without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Text?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4. S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> thought himſelfe in <hi>the bottome of the Deepe,</hi> remembring he had ſtollen his neighbors Peares. But the Apoſtate and his Teachers account ſuch ſleight matters veniall ſinnes, and ſay they are done away with knocking the breaſt, and holy water. Hee tranſlateth alſo
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:238:39"/>theſe words, <hi>in imo Abyſſi,</hi> in <hi>the bottome of Hell:</hi> as if God redeemed ſoules out of Hell, and Purgatorie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seruus fugiens Dominum, &amp; conſequut us vmbram, Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 7. he tranſlateth, <hi>a ſlaue flying his Lord, and finding nothing to lay hold vpon but a ſhadow.</hi> Where many words are redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, and the meaning not attained: for S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> meaning is, that a ſlaue flying, and obtaining a ſhadie place, had but a ſmall reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quis audet viribus ſuis tribuere castitatem &amp; innocentiam ſuam!</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 7. But this Apoſtate tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlateth it pedantically thus, <hi>Who dares preſume to entitle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the vertue of his chastitie and innocencie?</hi> quite beſide the Text: and this of purpoſe, leaſt S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſhould ſeeme to condemne his cooperations, and that power of Free-will which Pelagianizing Papiſts maintaine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Veni Carthaginem &amp; circumstrepebat me vndique ſartago flagitioſorum amorum,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 1. But the Apoſtate durſt not note any thing vpon the place, becauſe comming to <hi>Rome,</hi> he was boyled in a Frying-pan of impure &amp; flagitious Luſts, and reboyled againe in <hi>Cornelius</hi> Tub, and yet confeſſeth nothing, as did that holy Father.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. ſpeaketh of certaine Companions called <hi>Euer-ſores,</hi> or ouer-turners of Ciuilitie; a <hi>cruell and diuelliſh name:</hi> yet not ſo cruell, as the name of a Traytor, and Apoſtate, and a hyred ſlaue of Antichriſt. He compareth them to <hi>roaring Boyes, and Wittes:</hi> but <hi>Engliſh</hi> turned <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> are farre more cruell and diuelliſh.</p>
               <p>In the Margent of the fift Chapter he noteth, <hi>that there is great difficultie in vnderſtanding holy Scriptures;</hi> but quite contrarie to that holy Fathers meaning: for he ſayth, <hi>they profit ſuch as are little ones,</hi> and humble; albeit they be not vnderſtood of the proud and ignorant, ſuch as the Pope is, that preſumeth he cannot erre; and ſuch as his Diſciple here is, that with vnwaſhen hands and feet falleth vpon handling holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Manichees,</hi> as the Tranſlator ſayth in his Notes vpon
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:238:39"/>the 3. Booke of <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 6. <hi>profeſſed to beleeue the three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the holy Trinitie.</hi> But in the Text of S. <hi>Austine</hi> there is no ſuch matter: nay contrarie, hee ſayth, <hi>their heart was void of all truth.</hi> But did they beleeue ſome truth, yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the humanitie of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and forbidding Marriage to their elect Prieſts, and not receiuing the Cup in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and holding diuers other lewd fancies, they were groſſe Heretikes. Likewiſe are the Papiſts; who albeit they hold the Apoſtles Creed, yet hold theſe <hi>Manichean</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and thoſe of the <hi>Simonians, Carpocratians, Angelikes, Collyridians, Staurolatrians,</hi> and others. They teach alſo <hi>the fictions of Bodies, which haue no being at all,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth of them, <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> confeſſeth, he was perſwaded to yeeld to <hi>fooliſh Deceiuers;</hi> which he lamenteth, <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. Yet this Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate ſorroweth not, that he hath abandoned the Apoſtolike Faith, and yeelded to ſeducing Maſſe-Prieſts and Ieſuwides, teaching the Hereſies aboue mentioned, and diuers others: onely he noteth them to be Atheiſts, which (as it ſeemeth) diſlike, that the Pope ſhould allow that in one Age, which is vnlawfull in another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Flagitious ſinnes againſt nature,</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine, Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Conf. c.</hi> 8. deteſteth. He ſayth alſo, <hi>it is a generall agreement of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſocictie to obey Kings.</hi> Yet Popes diſturbe this generall agreement, forbidding men to obey Kings excommunicate, and his marked ſlaues clayme exemption from this obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: And many forſwearing Marriage, fall into theſe enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mious and flagitious ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Gladly would the Apoſtate, <hi>cap.</hi> 8. excuſe his companions, who in their Catechiſmes leaue out the ſecond Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, againſt I dols or grauen Images. But firſt, S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> leaueth out nothing: ſecondly, more Father diuide the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements into 4. in the firſt Table, and 6. in the laſt, then into 3. and 7. Thirdly, theſe words 3. and 7. ſeeme to haue crept into the Text, hauing no connexion with other words.</p>
               <p>In the 3. Booke and 9. Chap. the Apoſtate noteth, <hi>that in the Catholike Church there is no danger of indiſcretion, in doing
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:238:40"/>Penance.</hi> But firſt, moſt abſurdly he doteth, where he repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Pope, Cardinals, Maſſe-Prieſts, Monkes, and Fryars, to be the Catholike Church. S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> certes doth not talke of Popiſh Penance, in whipping themſelues, and lying on the ground, or on Ropes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Noli eſſe vana anima mea &amp; obſurdeſcere in aure cordis,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 11. And hereupon the Tranſlator noteth, <hi>That ſinne maketh vs deafe to the voyce of God.</hi> We may therefore well eſteeme, by his owne confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what the cauſe is why he heareth not the voyce of God, but rather heareth and followeth the call of Satan, drawing him away from the truth: his heart is deafe in hearing the Word, his ſoule fooliſh in obeying the voyce of Antichriſt, and delighting in forraine and ſtrange faſhions.</p>
               <p>He talketh alſo here of the <hi>Centre of Reſt,</hi> corrupting his Author, &amp; himſelfe being not only out of the Centre, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo all the Circumference of Reſt. In the Margent he noteth as an abſurditie, that <hi>any ſhould preferre the part before the whole.</hi> and yet he and his fellowes doe preferre the Pope before the Cardinals and Prieſts, and before the whole <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. <hi>When we relye on our ſelues,</hi> ſayth the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator, <hi>our ſtrength is nothing but meere weakeneſſe:</hi> A place ill tranſlated. S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> words are, <hi>Firmit as noſtra quando tu es, tunc eſt firmit as; cum autem noſtra eſt, infirmit as eſt.</hi> How then can man of himſelfe will or doe that is good, or prepare himſelfe to iuſtice, or before grace beleeue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and loue God?</p>
               <p>Where in the Text S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 1. hath, <hi>Heale thou all my Bones;</hi> the Tranſlator in the Margent noteth, <hi>the powers of his Soule:</hi> as if his Apoſtaticall Soule were full of Bones. S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> alſo ſayth, <hi>God doth open the heart when he will:</hi> Which ſheweth, that man cannot reſiſt his grace, nor receiue it, before it be giuen him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The picture of an Heretike,</hi> ſaith hee in a note vpon the 5. Booke and 6. <hi>Chap.</hi> is <hi>ſet out in</hi> Fauſtus, <hi>who was very ſhallow, albeit, hee made a faire ſhew.</hi> What then need wee goe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſeeke out an Heretike, then to this ſhallow-pated
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:238:40"/>Apoſtate, who notwithſtanding his ſhewes and brags, is a Tranſlator of ſmall ſubſtance, ſuch alſo are his pedanticall Maſters the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> that talking brauely of the Church and Tradition, runne their barkes vpon the ſands of the Popes Decrees, impudently bragging and yet performing nothing. Like to <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> who was <hi>Magnus laquens Diaboli,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Confeſ. c.</hi> 3. as they are.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Erat memoria B. Cypriani,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 8. This the Apoſtate tranſlateth, <hi>there was the Shrine of S.</hi> Cyprian. As if that godly Martyr were Shrined like <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> and worſhipped with Lights, Maſſes, Muſicke, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne acceſſe of Pilgrimes, and ſuch like Ceremonies. There alſo he ſaith, <hi>S.</hi> Cyprians <hi>Reliques were kept;</hi> but he ſheweth not what Reliques, nor is able to proue, that they were there worſhipped. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath no ſuch thing: It was onely a memory of <hi>Cyprians</hi> martyrdome. <hi>Monica</hi> there prayed to God, and not to <hi>Cyprian,</hi> as may bee collected out of S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> wordes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Manichees, as the Tranſlator noteth, <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued that our Sauiour</hi> CHRIST <hi>had not a naturall Body.</hi> And can hee and his conſorts beleeue otherwiſe, that in the Sacrament giue him a Body that is neyther felt nor ſeene, nor ſuffereth any thing? There alſo he addeth, <hi>that</hi> Monica <hi>went euery day to Maſſe,</hi> corrupting S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> wordes, who ſpeaketh of an Oblation no day <hi>pretermitted by her.</hi> But I trow the Apoſtate will not ſay ſhee ſayd Maſſe, neyther was there any Maſſe framed by <hi>Scholaſticus,</hi> or patched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by Popes in her time. <hi>Shee went euery day to Church,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaith: a plaine conuiction of Recuſants, that goe no day to Church.</p>
               <p>Hee addeth, <hi>that God by his promiſes maketh himſelfe a debtor;</hi> therefore for mens Merites hee is no debtor, remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting daily their debts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Manichees, as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> reporteth, <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 10. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued <hi>that God had the bulke of a Body.</hi> And doe not the <hi>Papiſts</hi> paint &amp; figure God the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, and giue them bulkes of bodies?</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:238:41"/>
               <p>As the <hi>Manichees</hi> ſalſified the Scriptures, as witneſſeth S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Confeſ. c.</hi> 11. So doe the Hereticall <hi>Papiſts</hi> both by Tranſlations and wicked Interpretations. 2. They doe alſo ſuppreſſe Gods eternall Teſtament, prohibitng the reading of it in vulgar Tranſlations without licence. 3. They falſifie the Fathers, as their Indexes, Expurgatory, and later Editions compared with Manuſcripts, and former Prints declare. In vaine therefore doth this poore Tranſlator thinke to wipe away ſo foule a fault, with a megre Margi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall note.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S.</hi> Ambroſe <hi>did Preach to the people,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> relateth, <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Confeſ. c.</hi> 13. hee <hi>did alſo ſubſtantially teach Saluation,</hi> whereas <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the Heretike <hi>did wander vp and downe by certaine fallacies.</hi> But the Pope and his proud Prelates Preach not. The Maſſe-Prieſts alſo and <hi>Ieſuwides,</hi> wandring in diuers fallacies and Schoole-trickes teach the Popes fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and leade their Diſciples out of the way of ſaluation, as did the Hereticall <hi>Manichees.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vpon the 5. Booke 14. <hi>Chap.</hi> in a Marginall note, he ſaith, <hi>God deceiueth men of their ſoules:</hi> moſt impiouſly making God a deceiuer, who deceiueth none, but draweth men by a right courſe into the way of Truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monica,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> teſtifieth, <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Confeſ. c.</hi> 2. <hi>brought Bread and Wine to the memories of Martyrs</hi> (which this jugler tranſlateth <hi>ſhrines</hi>) but was <hi>forbidden by the doore keeper: becauſe it was a Heatheniſh cuſtome.</hi> Yet this Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh cuſtome the heatheniſh Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> leaue not, Feaſting and Banquetting riotouſly on the feſtiuall dayes of their Saints, which they worſhip Idolatrouſly.</p>
               <p>The Tranſlator in a certaine Note doth inſinuate, that <hi>Ostiarius</hi> was then an Office in the Church, as it is now. But S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> doth neyther make an Order of Doore-kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, nor a Sacrament; nor can the Tranſlator with any Art draw that out of him. <hi>The Communion of the Body of our Lord,</hi> ſaith the holy Father, <hi>was celebrated at the Tombes of Martyrs.</hi> But neyther doth hee mention <hi>Maſſe,</hi> nor doe Maſſe-Prieſts alwayes make this Sacrament a Communion,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:238:41"/>eating and drinking all alone; albeit, this Iugler would willingly draw his Maſſe out of theſe Boxes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God hath no Children,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtate in <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Confeſ. c.</hi> 3. but <hi>ſuch as are members of the Catholike Church.</hi> How then can the Apoſtate and his fellowes claime to bee Gods children, being the members of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing forſaken the Catholike Church and Faith? S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>God ſpirituall Children</hi> are <hi>by him Regenerated by Grace.</hi> But the Apoſtate doth attribute Regeneration to the Prieſt and Sacrament, and that <hi>ex opere operato.</hi> Are they not then rather the Popes Baſtards, then Gods ſpirituall Children?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Perſuaſiſti mihi,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib. Confeſ.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>non qui crederent libris, quos tanta fere in omnibus gentibus autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate fundasti, ſed qui non crederent eſſe culpandos, nec audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endes eſſe ſi qui forte mihi dicerent, vnde ſcis illos libros vnius veri &amp; veraciſſimi Dei Spiritu humano generi eſſe miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos?</hi> So hee ſaith, firſt, that God perſwaded vs to beleeue holy Scriptures to bee of God. 2. That Scriptures haue their authority from God, and not from the Pope or Church. 3. That it is impious to make a queſtion how we know, that Scriptures came from God. But this falſe Tranſlator con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> wordes and meaning, maketh the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to receiue Authoritie from the Church in regard of vs. 2. He would haue vs to beleeue the Scriptures, not becauſe God perſwadeth vs, but becauſe the Church teacheth vs; as if the Church receiued her perſwaſion from herſelfe, and not from God. Laſtly, continually they queſtion vs how we know, that the Scriptures are of God; which this good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther condemneth as impious. To reſolue that the Scriptures are Diuine, becauſe the Pope ſaith ſo, is moſt ridiculous. The like fraud this Iugler vſeth in a Note vpon the 11. <hi>Cap.</hi> of this Booke, deriuing that Authority, which S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to holy Scriptures; to his Church, that is, to euery ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and faithleſſe Pope.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alipius</hi> is commended by <hi>S. Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>conf. c.</hi> 8. for that hee <hi>ſhut his eyes, leaſt hee ſhould behold the Gladiators;</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:238:42"/>intimating, that we are to auoid all occaſions of ſinne. Why then did not this Tranſlator ſhut his eyes in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> where are ſo many baits for ſinne? Did he drop into the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel blind-fold?</p>
               <p>In the Margent, <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 12. he telleth vs, that <hi>the Diuell is euer putting Tricks vpon him.</hi> And doe we maruell, that he and his fellowes are ſo lewd and vaine-glorious, ſeeing the Diuell doth put ſo many Tricks vpon them, and hath entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled their feet with his ſnares?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 13. he ſeemeth to inſiſt much vpon <hi>Viſions and Reuelations.</hi> But S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>Monicaes</hi> Viſions were <hi>vaine and fantaſticall,</hi> and that there was great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God reuealing, and the ſoule dreaming: And ſuch Dreames, commonly, are the Viſions and Reuelations of Monkes and Fryars. God therefore directeth vs, <hi>Iſay</hi> 8. to the Law and Teſtimonie, and not to Viſions nor the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of Spirits.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Concubine, as is related <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Conf. c.</hi> 11. <hi>vowed to God, ſhe would no more know man:</hi> ſo it may be, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny beaſtly women vow, they will forſake their lewd life. But this is but a ſimple argument to proue <hi>Vowes of Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> albeit the beſt the idle Tranſlator could draw out of Saint <hi>Auſtine;</hi> who yet hath nothing to ſay of Nuns, or their Rules.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 16. the Tranſlator noteth <hi>Merits</hi> in the Margent. But he is a poore diſputer, that out of ſuch Merits as <hi>Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> had, thinketh to prooue, that mens Workes doe merit eternall life. A fit man rather to follow Epicures, then to tranſlate good Bookes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 1. he placeth this profound Note in the margent, <hi>That the Catholike Church is our Mother.</hi> A point which no man doubteth. But if hee beleeue, that the Pope and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is the true Catholike Church or the Mother of faithfull Chriſtians, hee is foully miſtaken, not diſcerning the chaſte Spouſe of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> from the abominable Whore of <hi>Babilon.</hi> Further, when <hi>Rome</hi> was the Church, yet was ſhee but a particular Church.</p>
               <p>The cauſe of ſinne, is our owne will, as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> teacheth
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:238:42"/>vs, <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Conf. c.</hi> 3. And this that worthy man, M. <hi>Caluin,</hi> knew very well, who neuer ſaid nor thought as the damned Apoſtate chargeth him, <hi>that God maketh men to ſinne, that he may afterward damne them:</hi> neyther doth he ſay, that any doe ſinne by neceſſarie conſtraint. Theſe are the rayling Rinegates vaine and blaſphemous Conceits, and no Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of M. <hi>Caluin;</hi> as by the Texts by him falſely cited, may appeare.</p>
               <p>The Authoritie of the Church commendeth holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to particular perſons, as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 7. But he ſayth not, that holy Scriptures receiue their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie from the Catholike Church, as the Aduerſaries of the Church and Scriptures conceiue; and much leſſe, from the Pope, and Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> For if that were ſo, how could the Church beleeue Scriptures? May the Church authoriſe and deliuer Scriptures to it ſelfe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 18. S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> maketh <hi>Chriſt</hi> his only Mediator, ſhewing that hee was God and man. How then can the Schoole-men and their followers accord with him, making the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> together with Saints and Angels, to be Mediators, and holding that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is our Mediator <hi>according to his Humanitie only?</hi> That the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> being a Virgin ſtill, did conceiue and beare <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> is not doubted by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> it is alſo confeſſed, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was knowne to betrue man by Tradition, as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> teacheth, <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 19. But that this was knowne by Tradition vnwritten, &amp; onely, or that holy Scripture is knowne by Tradition, as the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator noteth, S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſayth not, neyther is it true: for the natures of <hi>Chriſt</hi> are knowne by Scripture, &amp; one Booke of Scripture teſtifieth of another. Neyther doth he ſay, that the holy Virgin was conceiued &amp; liued without ſin: theſe be only Friars fancies &amp; dreames, and not this holy Fathers doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We are to finde the ioyes of Heauen not without Penance in this life,</hi> ſayth the Tranſlator, worthie to be tranſlated, and made the Popes Penitentiarie, to impoſe Penance, and to giue pardon to all that are troubled with the Collick in their Braines. And this he noteth in <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 3. Yet S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:238:43"/>neuer thought, that the way to Heauen was by whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, knocking the breaſt, wearing hayre-cloth, and going bare-foot.</p>
               <p>Vpon the 8. Booke of <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 6. the Tranſlator noteth, <hi>that</hi> Anthonie <hi>the Aegyptian was a Monke, and that he wrought Miracles, and that there were many Monasteries before S.</hi> Auſtines <hi>time, and one neere Milan.</hi> But out of all theſe Monaſteries he cannot find one that held the Moderne Romiſh Religion, or that liued in obedience to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> or receiued their Rules from them. Further, they now worke no Miracles, nor are like to them eyther in their liues or ſtudies: nay, it appeareth they rather dwelt in Cells and poore Cottages, then in any ſumptuous Buildings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S.</hi> Anthonie <hi>and S.</hi> Auſtine <hi>were conuerted by reading holy Scriptures,</hi> as is teſtified <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 12. Why then are Chriſtians denyed libertie to reade holy Scriptures, in Tongues vnderſtood by them? Why are Scriptures repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be dumbe Teachers? Finally, why are Scriptures de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed to haue power to worke Faith, vnleſſe the Church pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them? Out of Scriptures certes, Monkiſh Vowes and their pretended Euangelicall perfection will neuer be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, albeit the Poſtiller ſhould reſolue himſelfe into ſweat, endcuoring to doe it. Theſe words, <hi>Goe and ſell all thou haſt,</hi> Matth. 19. <hi>and put on the Lord Jeſus,</hi> belong not to Monkes onely; nor did the <hi>Romans,</hi> or the young man in the Goſpel put on Monkes Cowles, vpon hearing theſe words. Finally, he that will find out the originall of Monkes and Fryars, he muſt ſearch not holy Scriptures, but the Popes Decretals.</p>
               <p>That man had free-will to do euill, S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> confeſſeth, <hi>Confeſs. Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 1. but that he had a power by free-will to doe well, that is a ſurmiſe of the Pelagianizing Tranſlator: for albeit grace moue vs to ſubmit our ſelues to <hi>Chriſts</hi> yoke, yet is it not our free-will that worketh what is good, but Gods grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>Conf. c.</hi> 2. the corrupter of S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Confeſſions endeuoreth to proue Graduall Verſes and Proceſſion out of them; but his labor is in vaine: he may as well out of them
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:238:43"/>draw from thence the Tricks of the Miſſall &amp; Breuiarie. But had the <hi>Jewes</hi> any ſuch Aſcenſion, or Proceſſion, yet are not the Traditions of the later <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Rabbins any warrant for him &amp; his Conſorts, to warrant their ſuperſtitious Deuices.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scripſi haec in Caera,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Austine, Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 4. And this the Buzzard tranſlateth, <hi>This I wrote in Waxe.</hi> As if men did then write in Waxe, and not in Tables layd ouer with Waxe, mixed with other ſtuffe: ſo he thinketh they wrote <hi>in Dust,</hi> where the Writing was on Tables plaſtred ouer with Waxe and Duſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That men went bare-foot in Deuotion,</hi> S. <hi>Austine</hi> doth not affirme, albeit this thred-bare Tranſlator doth hold that to be a cuſtome vſed, <hi>Confeſſ. Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 6. Nay, he doth account ſuch bare-footed Walkers to be rather Heretikes, then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout Chriſtians, <hi>Lib. de Haereſ. c.</hi> 68.</p>
               <p>The Bodies of two Martyrs, as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> relateth, <hi>Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>Conf. c.</hi> 7. were found at <hi>Milan:</hi> but neyther were thoſe Bodies worſhipped, nor did thoſe Martyrs hold any Article of the Doctrine of <hi>Trent,</hi> denyed by vs. Miracles might be wrought at theſe Martyrs Sepulchre; but neyther doth Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſay, that Martyrs wrought thoſe Miracles, nor doth the Apoſtate beleeue all the Miracles that are written in Saints Legends, if he be in his right ſences.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Placito ſancto ſimul habitabamus,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 8. ſpeaking of <hi>Euodius</hi> and himſelfe. Out of which, the Tranſlator noteth, <hi>that they entred into a Religious life;</hi> by which, he vnderſtandeth Monaſticall profeſſion: as if S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> turned Monke, and knew no other Religious life, but that of Monkes and Fryars; which was not then vſed, and is now moſt irreligious.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. he ſayth, <hi>S.</hi> Auſtine <hi>and his Mother were in an extaſie;</hi> extatically and fanatically belying his Author, who ſpeaketh not one word to that purpoſe. Theſe words alſo, <hi>Attigimus cam modice toto ictu cordis, &amp; ſuſpirauimus, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquimus ibi religatas primitias Spiritus,</hi> he tranſlateth thus, <hi>We grew able to take a little taſte thereof with the whole ſtrife of our ſoules, and we ſighed profoundly, and left there confined
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:238:44"/>the very top and flower of our ſoules and ſpirits.</hi> But in the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, there is no word ſignifying our abilitie to taſte Gods wiſdome, nor is our ſtrife <hi>ictus cordis,</hi> nor can the Tranſlator tell what is <hi>the top and flower of mens ſoules:</hi> The <hi>firſt fruits of the Spirit,</hi> words vſed by S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> ſignifie another thing.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Monica</hi> died, <hi>ſhe deſired to be remembred at the Lords Altar,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>Conf. c.</hi> 11. But <hi>that her ſonne ſhould pray for her,</hi> ſhe deſired not, albeit this Rine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate doth impudently affirme it in his falſe gloſſe. Further, neyther did S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> beleeue, that her ſoule was in Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, nor did any Maſſe-Prieſt ſing Maſſe for her; her name was only rehearſed out of the Church Tables, that all might know and remember ſhe dyed a faithfull Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conuenerunt fratres &amp; religioſae foeminae,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 12. But not a Fryar, or Nunne, as this hungrie Hinde imagineth, gaping for ſome Reliques of Poperie, which he cannot draw out of S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> words: for that Vermine came not into the World, vntill the time of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third; and theſe, that came together, were Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian men and women, that were to conduct and prepare the Corps to the Funerall.</p>
               <p>The Tranſlator ſayth, <hi>The Sacrifice of the Maſſe was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for S.</hi> Monica, <hi>being dead.</hi> But S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> mentioneth no Maſſe; nor by the Sacrifice of our Seruice offered for her, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth any thing but the commemoration of her name, made in the holy Myſteries, called a Sacrifice, becauſe it was a memoriall of Chriſts Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> prayed for his Mother out of his affection, and in regard of her more ſpeedie reſurrection and glorification, but not to draw her ſoule out of Purgatorie, as Papiſts doe: for he doubted not, but God had performed what he deſired before, as he ſayth, <hi>Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>Credo iam feceris quod te rogo,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>ſed voluntaria oris mei approba Domine.</hi> He doth alſo deſire others to remember his Father and Mother at the Lords Altar, but not to pray for their ſoules in Purgatorie, as this Prodigall, that is not well purged nor perfumed for his ſcabs, and other vncleaneſſe, would haue it.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:238:44"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 10. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 3. he condemneth Auricular confeſſion made to Prieſts in the <hi>Roman</hi> Synagogue; <hi>What haue I to doe with men,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>that they ſhould heare my Confeſſions, as if they could cure my Languors:</hi> manifeſtly he denyeth both the neceſſitie of Confeſſion, and the power of Maſſe-Prieſts Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. But this is paſſed by in ſilence, without any note or obſeruation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 4. the Poſtiller denyeth not, that S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> was <hi>certaine of his ſaluation:</hi> Why ought not then others alſo to endeuor to make their election ſure? He ſayth, <hi>he wrought it in feare and trembling:</hi> as if men could not feare Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and yet aſſure themſelues of his gracious promiſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou haſt ſtrucken my heart with thy Word, and I haue loued thee,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 10. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 6. But this Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator regardeth not Gods Word, neyther is ſo in loue with God; but hee loueth the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the Curti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zans of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> much more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 10. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 31. S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> taketh away all diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Meates, teaching, that <hi>to the cleane all things are cleane,</hi> and that <hi>all Gods creatures are good, if they be taken with thanksgiuing.</hi> But the falſe Poſtiller addeth an Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that <hi>they are ſometimes to be deuoutly forborne, when the Church commandeth vs to faſt.</hi> An Exception not only beſide but contrarie to S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> words and meaning, who neuer knew any ſuch Church, as prohibited fleſh and white meats, nor any ſuch prohibition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No man can be certaine of his ſaluation, according to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of</hi> S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> ſayth the Poſtiller, <hi>Lib.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 32. but moſt falſely. He ſayth only, <hi>Nemo ſecurus eſſe debet,</hi> that is, <hi>None ought to be careleſſe:</hi> ſo do we alſo beleeue, &amp; teach. But Gods promiſe, he ſayth, <hi>is firme and faithfull;</hi> and acknowledgeth, that <hi>his only hope &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence is in Gods faithful promiſe &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: Vna ſpes, vna fiducia, vna firma promiſſio miſericordia tua.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 34. <hi>lib.</hi> 10. he ſayth <hi>Eſau bleſſed his ſonnes,</hi> miſtaking <hi>Eſau</hi> for <hi>Iſaac,</hi> as it is both in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and S. <hi>Auſtine:</hi> ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had he ſo much grace as to correct this foule fault, albeit he amended many ſleight eſcapes.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:238:45"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 35. hee giueth the title of <hi>Spirituall perſons</hi> to Maſſe-Prieſts, Monkes, and Fryars, moſt abſurdly; for they are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten more carnall then ſpirituall, and Lay-men are led by the ſpirit more then they.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 39. in a certaine Marginall Note, he ſayth, <hi>Chriſt died for all,</hi> albeit S. <hi>Austine</hi> ſay no ſuch thing: nay contrarie, holy Scriptures teach vs, that few are choſen; and that he is the Sauior of his Body, and came not to ſaue the reprobate, but his owne people, for whom alſo he prayed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tantum conſuetudinis ſarcina degrauat,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auguſtine, Lib. Confeſſ.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 40. This burthen of euill Cuſtome, the Tranſlator ſuppoſeth to be <hi>euill Habits:</hi> which is farre wide from S. <hi>Austines</hi> meaning, and from the ſignification of the word; <hi>Habits</hi> being qualities inherent, and <hi>Cuſtome</hi> a practiſe incident. The Tranſlator hath a cuſtome to lye, and to talke idly, and to tranſlate falſely, yet are they no habits in him.</p>
               <p>Fryars and Monkes doe vſually pretend Extaſies; but this was no practiſe of S. <hi>Auſtine.</hi> His Marginall Note therefore vpon the 40. chapter of the 10. Booke of Confeſſions, might well haue beene ſpared; where he ſayth, <hi>he was plunged into high and deepe Extaſies,</hi> albeit there be no words of any ſuch matter in the Text. Nay, S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſheweth he was poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with <hi>inward feeling, and delight;</hi> which haue no place, when a man is depriued of his ſences.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All ſinfull pleaſure,</hi> ſayth the Apoſtate, apoſtilling the 41. chapter, <hi>is a Lye;</hi> yet his Author affirmeth no ſuch thing: neyther is it a Lye, that the Apoſtate taketh ſinfull pleaſure in lying and rayling.</p>
               <p>No Angel, ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 10. <hi>Conf. c.</hi> 42. <hi>could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile vs to God.</hi> To ſalue this ſore, the Tranſlator in the Margent forgeth this euaſion, <hi>that he ſpeaketh not of interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but of redemption.</hi> But S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> in plaine words re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecteth interceſſion of Angels, as well as Redemption. <hi>Was I,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>to reſort to Angels? By what Prayers? By what Sacraments?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 43. he ſayth, <hi>he thought to flye into the Deſart: but God for bad him.</hi> Yet this ignorant Gull and his brutiſh Conſorts
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:238:45"/>doe giue out, that he was the Patron and Founder of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miticall and Hypocriticall Fryars, and a Preacher to Monks in the Wilderneſſe; and haue forged a number of Sermons in his name, <hi>ad fratres in Eremo.</hi> This Poſtiller ſayth, <hi>The Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites life is a holy ſtate;</hi> but his braine, when he ſo wrote, was not in right ſtate: S. <hi>Austine,</hi> his Leader, ſaid no ſuch thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 11. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 2. the holy Doctor ſheweth <hi>how he was drawne by Gods exhortations, terrors, conſolations, and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, to preach his Word, and diſpenſe his Sacraments to the people.</hi> And are they then lawfully called, that being ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Biſhops by Antichriſt, preach not? And being made Prieſts, offer for quicke and dead, and preach Fables in ſtead of Gods Word? That diſpence not the Sacraments to the people, but eate and drinke all alone?</p>
               <p>There alſo he deſireth, <hi>that the holy Scriptures may be made his chast delight.</hi> But the Tranſlator and his Teachers care little for Chaſtitie, and leſſe for holy Scriptures, being more occupyed about vnwritten Traditions, Schoole ſubtleties, and the Popes Decretals.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The words of Scriptures,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine, haue deere retyring into them, walking, feeding, and lying in them:</hi> by <hi>deere,</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all ſorts of Chriſtians, and not greaſie Prieſts and graduated Doctors, as the Apoſtate would haue it; for <hi>deere</hi> tranſlating <hi>Stagges,</hi> and vnderſtanding the ſtalion Prieſts, as if they onely were to reade and ſtudie Scriptures.</p>
               <p>In the Margent the Tranſlator noteth <hi>that Prieſts and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, by a moſt choiſe and noble Metaphor, are called Stagges,</hi> and thereby would exclude Lay men and women from rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Scriptures. But were his Prieſts and Monkes <hi>Stagges</hi> and <hi>Stalions</hi> to, yet S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> doth not appropriate the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Scriptures to them, nor debarre others from reading them. The Apoſtles wrote as well to people, as to Prieſts: And <hi>Hiero'me</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86. calling them <hi>Scripturas populorum,</hi> ſheweth, they belong to the people, as well as Prieſts. But, ſayth the Apoſtate, <hi>It is an eaſie thing, by reading of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to bedeceiued, and to deceiue others.</hi> But quite beſide that holy Fathers meaning, that miſliked not the reading, but the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:238:46"/>miſ-vnderſtanding of them; and therefore prayed, <hi>that he might not be deceiued in them,</hi> by miſtaking them, as the Popes Factors doe. In the end teaching, <hi>that Christ intercedes for vs,</hi> he oueithroweth the Popiſh interceſſion of Saints.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 3. He confeſſeth, <hi>if</hi> Moſes <hi>ſpoke in Hebrew, hee ſhould not vnderſtand him.</hi> But the Apoſtate contradicting his Author ſaith, <hi>he had ſome skill in Hebrew.</hi> Declaring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be a Contradictor, and no Tranſlator.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 8. doth call <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeaking to vs in his holy Goſpell, <hi>his good and only Maſter.</hi> But the Apoſtate and his Confreres, hold the Pope to be their only and chiefe and good Maſter, neyther regarding <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nor his Goſpell, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the Pope be pleaſed to propoſe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 31. the Tranſlator talketh idely of <hi>Habits and Cuſtomes,</hi> where S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> nameth only the <hi>Conſequences of ſinnes,</hi> which follow euill Cuſtomes and actions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 1. The holy Father doth not ſpeake one word of <hi>the diſſiculty of holy Scripture.</hi> See then the audacious bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Tranſlator, that maketh that the title of the <hi>Chapter.</hi> S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> contrary, proueth the facility out of <hi>Chriſts</hi> promiſe, ſaying; <hi>ſeeke and you ſhall find: knocke, and it ſhall bee opened vnto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſame Booke <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. the fooliſh Tranſlator tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth much of <hi>Materia prima,</hi> which is not ſo much as once named there by S. <hi>Auſtine.</hi> And <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. hee ſpeaketh of an <hi>Imperiall Heauen,</hi> oppoſed <hi>to a Corporiall Heauen.</hi> It may be he meaneth to giue the Dominion of the Heauen to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, and afterward to ſubiect both the Emperor and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the Pope. Where note I pray you the Ideots igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, who writeth <hi>Imperial</hi> for <hi>Empyreal,</hi> or fiery, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth Fire and the Heauen to be no bodies.</p>
               <p>In a marginall Note vpon the 12. <hi>Bocke,</hi> 11. <hi>Chap.</hi> the Tranſlator mentioneth <hi>Quires of Angels?</hi> where S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> neyther mentioneth <hi>Quires,</hi> nor Orders of <hi>Angels.</hi> So ſaucy he is, as to change S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> words &amp; meaning, to eſtabliſh his own fooliſh Popiſh conceits. <hi>Et per inania cordis ſui cum ſuis phantaſmatibus vagatur &amp; voluitur,</hi> and <hi>by the vanities
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:238:46"/>of his heart, with his phantaſies hee wandreth and tumbleth,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſayth in that place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 13. The Tranſlator <hi>by Heauen and Earth.</hi> will needs vnderſtand <hi>the Angels,</hi> and <hi>Materia prima.</hi> But S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> whom he ſhould follow hath no ſuch wordes. And abſurdly Earth is called <hi>Materia prima,</hi> and Angels confounded with Heauen. Hereof we may better inferre that the Tranſlators <hi>Materia prima</hi> is foolery and confuſion, and his Heauen, his owne vayne imagination and the Popes conſiſtory.</p>
               <p>Vpon euery Woman that readeth Scripture, hee rayleth, calling her <hi>Saucy and ſimple, Lib.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 14. not ſparing his owne Mother. As if <hi>Engliſh</hi> women reading Scriptures without the Popes licence, were more ſaucy then <hi>Jtalian, French</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> women, reading Legends and liuing in Brothels, by whom, they ſay, he hath beene euil-fauouredly dreſſed and ſauced.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 15. doth plainly declare, that men are not juſtified by their Workes or qualities inherent. <hi>Nos dicti ſumus,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>juſtitia tua, ait enim quidam ſeruus tuus, vt nos ſimus juſtitia Dei in ipſo. We are called thy juſtice. for a Seruant of thine ſaith, that wee may be made the righteouſneſſe of God in him.</hi> Was not the Poſtiller then blind and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, that out of the Fathers words inferred, that there is inherent Iuſtice in men. For how can Gods juſtice, that is in him, be inherent in vs, or our inherent Iuſtice be the perfect Iuſtice of God? Angels may haue true light in themſelues becauſe they fell not; but Man being fallen, can neyther haue perfect Light, nor Iuſtice in him; but muſt be juſtified by Faith in CHRIST.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In culmine ſequendae aut horitatis nobiſcum conſtituentis illam per Sanctam</hi> Moyſem <hi>editam ſanctam Scripturam tuam,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 12. <hi>Confeſ. c.</hi> 16. that is, <hi>placing holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures written by holy</hi> Moſes <hi>on the top of Authority to bee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</hi> Was not then this Rinegate impudent, that tooke the Authority, which S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> beſtowed on Scriptures, and by a tricke of Legierdemaine conueyed it to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to euery blind Pope?</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:238:47"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>That one place of Scripture hath diuers ſences,</hi> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate blindly auoweth in his Notes on the 12. Booke of S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Confeſſions, <hi>Chap.</hi> 18. hee ſhall neuer bee able to proue by the teſtimony of that Father, who confirmeth that to be the ſence of Scripture, which the Enditor meant, who is Truth, and ſpeaketh but one thing. Thus wee ſee, for a Tranſlator, we haue here a corrupter &amp; falſifier of S. <hi>Auſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Afterward, <hi>lib.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 20. he ſayth, diuers Expoſitors may diuerſly interprete one place; but he ſayth not, <hi>that one place hath diuers ſences,</hi> as the Apoſtate, without all ſence, infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. For how can that which differeth, be true? And how can God in one ſentence vnderſtand diuers things, he being alwayes one, and vnchangeable?</p>
               <p>The Poſtiller vpon the Margent of this 12. Booke, <hi>c.</hi> 25. ſayth, <hi>Truth is a Catholike Benediction;</hi> and S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> there confeſſeth, that <hi>Truth belongeth not to any one man, but is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all the louers of Truth.</hi> But he is an abſurd fellow, to ſuppoſe the Pope and his followers, embracing the refuſe Doctrine of <hi>Trent,</hi> and the Schooles, to be Catholikes; or Truth to be a Benediction beſtowed on Papiſts, that wee haue found and declared to be forgers, lyars, ſlanderers, and a packe of Heretikes. Further, if Truth belongeth not to any one man, why doth euery falſe Pope, that is but a priuat man, pretend, that he is the onely ſupreme Iudge of Truth, and infallible interpreter of holy Scriptures?</p>
               <p>In the Title of the 30. chapter of the 12. Booke of S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> Confeſſions, the Tranſlator ſayth, <hi>Charitie is to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained among men of contrarie opinions.</hi> So hee pronounceth ſentence againſt the Pope, and his Inquiſitors, and all their Faction, which perſecute Chriſtians, and cut their throats, for not holding euery one of their trifling Hereſies.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> would haue <hi>Truth to make friends:</hi> But the Apoſtaticall Sect will not heare him, being offended for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, then that we teach Truth againſt the Brood of Antichriſt, and their wicked Errors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 13. <hi>Confeſs. c.</hi> 1. the Poſtiller noteth, <hi>that without Gods inſpiration, a man cannot thinke a good thought:</hi> which is alſo
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:238:47"/>S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Doctrine; and both, contrary to the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Doctrine of Papiſts, that giue free-will to a naturall man both to ſay well, and to doe well.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. the Tranſlator intimateth, that man riſeth from ſinne, and is iuſtified by the helpe of Charitie inherent in vs. And this he endeuoreth to picke out of S. <hi>Auſtine;</hi> but ſooner ſhall hee picke Gudgeons out of Flint ſtones: for that holy Father doth not ſpeake there of Charitie inherent in vs, but of Charitie gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs, and working in vs by Gods holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 9. ridiculouſly he endeuoreth to proue his Popiſh Proceſſion, by the example of the <hi>Jewes;</hi> who, as he ſayth, did ſing Pſalmes <hi>as they went vp the ſtayres of the Temple.</hi> As if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Maſſe-Prieſt, ſinging Letanies as they goe vp <hi>Newgate</hi> ſtayres, or as they goe to <hi>Tiburne,</hi> doe walke in Proceſſion. By the Pſalmes of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> this Apoſtate will neuer proue his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanies, or Proceſſion, for they ſung Pſalmes to God; Maſſe-Prieſts, in their Letanies, pray to dead men.</p>
               <p>Where S. <hi>Auſtine, lib.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 13. ſpeaketh of the <hi>expectation of adoption, and the redemption of his body,</hi> the falſe Poſtiller no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that S. <hi>Paul ſaued Chriſtians, by praying for them after his glorification;</hi> of which, that Father giueth not the leaſt ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: nay contrarie, he expected the fruits of his owne adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the redemption of his owne bodie; of which, other Chriſtians were no members.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. he ſayth, <hi>the</hi> Caluiniſts <hi>affirme their Church to conſist only of the elect.</hi> But the lying Apoſtate ſheweth not who theſe <hi>Caluiniſts</hi> are, and where they write ſo much as he chargeth them with. <hi>Caluin</hi> himſelfe ſaith only, that the Catholike Church is a Communion of Saints, and properly conſiſteth of the Elect to whom remiſſion of ſins &amp; eternall life belong, albeit many wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men may ſeeme to be of the Catholike Church, &amp; in regard of their profeſſion are reputed members of particular Churches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quis niſi tu Deus noſter feciſti nobis firmamentum authoritatis ſuper nos in ſcriptura tua diuina,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 13. <hi>Confeſ. c.</hi> 1.5. that is, <hi>who but thou our God hath giuen vs a foundation of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aboue vs in thy diuine Scripture?</hi> which clearely refuteth the blaſphemous Poſtill of this Apoſtate, who ſaith the <hi>Church</hi> (that is the Pope) <hi>hath power to make Scriptures Canonicall to vs.</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:238:48"/>For if they receiue authority from God only, how commeth the Pope or the Church to giue them authority? and how doth the Church know them to be Canonicall, but by diuine Authority?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 19. the Tranſlator corrupteth S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> text, by adding to it about the middle of the <hi>Chap.</hi> theſe words, <hi>a word of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell:</hi> following as it ſeemeth his <hi>Spaniſh</hi> notes and tranſlation. He intimateth alſo, that <hi>Fryers and Monkes</hi> the ſcum and refuſe of the world, are <hi>an elected generation,</hi> which S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> neyther meant, nor could ſpeake of. Finally, he ſaith, <hi>Religious men and Prieſts are a middle kind of Creatures,</hi> as you would ſay, Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taures, Satyrs, &amp; Monſters, being neither Saints (&amp; therfore not belonging to the <hi>Church</hi> that is a Communion of Saints) nor or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and therefore not belonging to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or to the King, becauſe they clayme themſelues to bee exempt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By creeping things, Confeſ. lib.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 20. the Poſtiller vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Maſſe-Prieſts, Monkes, &amp; Friers: who indeed creepe and crawle like Snakes, leape like Toades, and ſwarme like Lice. But yet hee is much deceiued, if he thinke there were any ſuch ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine in the world in S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 21. the Tranſlator ſeeketh for Maſſe-Prieſts, Monks and Friers in S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> and in the 1. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> declaring that <hi>they are men as it were ſeuered from the world.</hi> But the poore I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deot is as farre wide, as <hi>Geneſis</hi> is from the <hi>Apocalipſe,</hi> where he may find Locuſts newly come out of the bottomleſſe pit, and Maſſe-Prieſts are no where found, but in the Popes Decretals and Pontificall. Both moſt noxious Serpents, and giuen to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality and worldly pleaſures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spirituales ergo ſiue qui praeſunt, ſiue qui obtemperant ſpirituali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter iudicant,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Auſtine, Lib.</hi> 13. <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 23. that is, <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall men iudge, whether they rule or obey:</hi> but of the <hi>ſublime authoritie of Gods Booke</hi> he will admit none to iudge, but would haue all men to <hi>ſubmit their vnderſtanding vnto it.</hi> How then doth the Pope take vpon him to be that ſpirituall man that iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth all things? Can <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight, <hi>c. vnam ſanctam, extr. com. de Maior. &amp; Obed.</hi> iudge better then S. <hi>Auſtine?</hi> What audacious boldneſſe is it for euery Pope, to challenge a power to himſelfe ouer Scriptures, to make them authenticall to vs? Euery Preacher may expound Scriptures, but the Pope challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:238:48"/>a power to authorize Scriptures; which this Apoſtate alſo would auow, if he durſt: but S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> doth beat downe both the Apoſtates and the Popes blaſphemous pride. <hi>Fiſh,</hi> he ſayth, <hi>is ſometimes a figure of Chriſt in the Sacrament:</hi> a proper deuice. For ſo the Prieſts, by their Tranſubſtantiation, make of Bread Fleſh, and this Apoſtiller by a new figure will make it Fiſh, that they may haue in the ſame Feaſt both Fiſh and Fleſh: Matters neuer though of by S. <hi>Auſtine.</hi> Neyther doth he in this place by bleſſing and calling vpon God, vnderſtand croſſing or ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of holy Water, ſuch as Maſſe-Prieſts vſe, but bleſſing and prayſing the Name of God.</p>
               <p>In his Notes vpon the 13. Booke of <hi>Confeſſions, c.</hi> 25. he <hi>would be glad to know,</hi> as he ſayth, <hi>what Benedictions haue come vnto vs from our Miniſters, and whether their ſound be gone ouer all the Earth.</hi> And I, to giue him ſatisfaction, anſwere, That theſe Bleſſings we receiue from them: We learne to know God, and whom he hath ſent, Chriſt Ieſus, and to diſcerne Antichriſt, and to flye from him: We learne the true Faith, and Gods true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: We vnderſtand, that we are to auoid the Hereſies of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, and her abominable Idolatry and Superſtition: We learne how to reforme our liues, and walke worthie our profeſſion. But of him and his Maſſe-Prieſts, Monkes, and Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, ignorant people receiue nothing but an implicite Faith, Croſſes, Beades, holy Water, Maſſes, <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> Indulgences, and ſuch Toyes: neyther doe they learne any thing, except that which we teach, but Hereſie, Superſtition, Idolatry, Rebellion, ignorance of Scripture, and corruption of manners, nor receiue any thing but ſhame. Biſhops made by the Pope, preach not, Maſſe-Prieſts teach little, Monkes and Fryars teach without authoritie, hauing no power but from Antichriſt; and if they teach any Truth, it is mixed with many Errors and Corruptions. That which we teach, is the Apoſtles Doctrine, the ſound of whoſe Doctrine is gone ouer the whole Earth; the Papiſts Hereſies, and falſe Doctrine, is onely receiued in the Popes Iuriſdiction.</p>
               <p>Our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> promiſeth to <hi>him that receiueth a Prophet in his name, the reward of a Prophet,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>Confeſſ. lib.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 26. But abſurdly is this applyed to Maſſe-Prieſts, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:238:49"/>ſuch falſe Prophets: for ſuch deſtroy Soules, vndermine the State, corrupt the Manners of their Diſciples, and ſeeke onely to vnderprop the ruinous Kingdome of Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 34. S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>God hath ſolidely built the authoritie of his Booke</hi> (of Scriptures) <hi>betweene ſuperiors which ſhould learne of God, and inferiors which ſhould be ſubiect vnto them: Solidasti authoritatem libri tui inter ſuperiors qui tibi docibiles eſſent, &amp; inferiores qui eis ſubderentur.</hi> So he giueth au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to Scriptures, and would haue all men ſubiect vnto them: which is contrarie to this Apoſtates mind. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by his falſe Notes he goeth about to corrupt the place, not willing to denie the Popes authoritie, in making Scriptures Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall to vs by that authoritie; contrarie to S. <hi>auſtines</hi> iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which would haue Superiors to learne of God. He ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth alſo, that <hi>the Scripture is ſubiect to the expoſition of Doctors;</hi> which is contrarie to that holy Fathers meaning.</p>
               <p>Finally, S. <hi>Auſtine, lib.</hi> 13. <hi>Conf. c.</hi> 38. hopeth to reſt in Gods holy place, which he calleth <hi>his great ſanctificaton;</hi> not for his merites, but by Gods grace and mercie. And this doe all good Catholikes hope, and beleeue: not doubting of their ſaluation, grounded on his holy Word, that is moſt certaine; and his ſweet Promiſes, that are moſt comfortable. But this Apoſtate and his peruerſe companions neyther beleeuing that Gods Word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth them, nor truſting to his Promiſes, made to all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue and liue according to their holy profeſſion, nor hauing good conſcience nor feeling of the holy Ghoſt, but meaſure all by their owne workes and merites, are neyther Catholikes, nor <hi>Chriſts</hi> Diſciples.</p>
               <p>And this, I truſt, will ſuffice to vindicate the holy Father Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> from the violence and wrong offered to him by this impure Apoſtate. As for the wrong that he hath offered to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I truſt our Superiors will in time vindicate: and albeit they neglect it, or cannot redreſſe it, I doubt not but God will reuenge his owne Cauſe his owne ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deo vni trino laus honor gloria in ſempiterna ſecula. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:238:49"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
